<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
  <info>
    <title>XSLTForms for the ‘20s</title>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>XSLTForms</keyword>
      <keyword>XForms</keyword>
      <keyword>XSLT</keyword>
      <keyword>XQuery</keyword>
      <keyword>HTML</keyword>
      <keyword>CSS</keyword>
      <keyword>Javascript</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <abstract>
      <para>Since 2009, XSLTForms has been developed with support for old
      browsers. It is now time to consider modern browsers and XForms 2.0
      support with XPath/XQuery 2.0+ instead of XPath 1.0</para>
    </abstract>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Alain</firstname><surname>Couthures</surname></personname>

      <personblurb>
        <para>Alain Couthures is a non-conventional expert programmer finding
        solutions to problems many would not even imagine being resolvable. He
        has already implemented XForms at client-side (XSLTForms) and is also
        implementing XQuery in Javascript. He is a member of the W3C XForms
        Users Community Group.</para>
      </personblurb>

      <email>alain.couthures@agencexml.com</email>
      <affiliation><orgname>agenceXML</orgname></affiliation>
    </author>
  </info>

  <para>More and more complex forms are to be used but do they all work as
  users would like? XForms is remaining as a nice declarative approach to
  allow authors, even without strong programming abilities, to write robust
  forms. XSLTForms is a light XForms implementation for browsers, at client
  side.</para>

  <section>
    <title>XSLTForms since 2009</title>

    <para>XSLTForms <citation>XSLTForms</citation> has been compatible with successive browser versions
    starting from Internet Explorer 4. It is based on XSLT 1.0, CSS and
    vanilla Javascript. Consequently, XSLTForms is composed of 3 files:
    <filename>xsltforms.xsl</filename>, <filename>xsltforms.css</filename>
    and <filename>xsltforms.js</filename>.</para>

    <para>This XSLT stylesheet acts as a compiler, generating both HTML
    elements with a bunch of CSS classes and Javascript instructions. The
    complex part in it is the XPath 1.0 parser.</para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:input ref="PersonGivenName" incremental="true">
 <xf:label>Please enter your first name: </xf:label>
</xf:input>]]></programlisting>

    <para>Becomes</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<span id="xsltforms-mainform-input-4_4_2_" class="xforms-disabled xforms-control xforms-input xforms-appearance">
 <span class="focus"> </span>
 <label for="xsltforms-mainform-input-input-4_4_2_" id="xsltforms-mainform-label-2_4_4_2_" class="xforms-label">Please enter your first name: </label>
 <span class="value">
  <input type="text" id="xsltforms-mainform-input-input-4_4_2_" incremental="true" class="xforms-value" />
 </span>
 <span class="xforms-required-icon">*</span>
 <span class="xforms-alert">
  <span class="xforms-alert-icon"> </span>
 </span>
</span>]]></programlisting>

    <para>And</para>

    <programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[XsltForms_xpath.create(xsltforms_subform,"PersonGivenName",false,
 new XsltForms_locationExpr(false,
  new XsltForms_stepExpr('child',
   new XsltForms_nodeTestName('','PersonGivenName')
  )
 )
);
new XsltForms_input(xsltforms_subform,xsltforms_subform.id + "-input-4_4_2_",2,"text",
 new XsltForms_binding(null, "PersonGivenName"),null,"true",null,null,null
);]]></programlisting>

    <para>XForms 1.1 Recommendation <citation>XF11</citation> is based on XPath 1.0: no sequences, no
    <code>eq</code>, <code>ne</code>, <code>lt</code>, … operators, no types, ... XSLTForms has its own XPath 1.0
    engine in two steps: the parser written in XSLT 1.0 and the evaluator
    written in Javascript. It is frustrating for authors used to retrieve data
    from XML databases to be restricted to XPath 1.0 while XQuery/XPath 4.0 is
    now emerging.</para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[concat('Hello ', PersonGivenName, '. We hope you like XForms!')]]></programlisting>

    <para>Becomes</para>

    <programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[new XsltForms_functionCallExpr('http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions concat',
 new XsltForms_cteExpr('Hello '),
 new XsltForms_locationExpr(false,
  new XsltForms_stepExpr('child',
   new XsltForms_nodeTestName('','PersonGivenName')
  )
 ),
 new XsltForms_cteExpr('. We hope you like XForms!')
)]]></programlisting>

    <para>For generating Javascript instructions, XSLT 1.0 is not a very nice
    approach because of a rather limited function set and just named templates
    to process strings. For example, performance is not good with very long
    element names… When applied at client-side, the XSLT stylesheet execution
    results in a blank-page effect before HTML elements being rendered.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Browsers have evolved</title>

    <para>XSLT 1.0 is still available on major browsers but some smartphones
    don’t have it. Some browser vendors would be happy removing their XSLT
    engine just to gain memory. They usually argue that XSLT 1.0 is not
    significantly used in websites. And Mozilla Firefox own XSLT 1.0 engine
    bugs won’t be fixed…</para>

    <para>HTML, CSS and Javascript have evolved significantly to HTML5, CSS3
    and ECMAScript 6 and browsers support many of their features which allows
    more powerful programming.</para>

    <para>Machines are faster and Javascript is more and more optimized for
    performance.</para>

    <para>Vanilla Javascript can still be a pertinent choice because even once
    famous Javascript frameworks come and go while others don’t bother with
    ascending compatibility… They do not seem to be really interested in
    performance either.</para>

    <para>By the way, Node.js appeared so vanilla Javascript can also run
    outside a browser. Just using it, it is very easy to run an HTTP server on
    a local machine: Node.js can be used to interact with files, databases and
    so on while XForms is interacting with users.</para>

    <para>All these evolutions allow XSLTForms modernization to be declined in
    the following axes:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>An HTML5 notation for XForms elements and CSS styling of
        them</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>An XQuery/XPath 3.1 parser written in Javascript</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>An XQueryX 3.1 to Javascript transpiler</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>XForms 2.0 <citation>XF2</citation> is also in good progress and XSLTForms should support all
    its features as well.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>HTML5 notation for XForms elements and CSS styling</title>

    <para>XSLTForms is now using an HTML5 notation for XForms elements
    replacing numerous <tag>DIV</tag> and <tag>SPAN</tag> embedded elements
    with only CSS classes to differentiate them. This is still performed with
    XSLT 1.0 but it can also be done with vanilla Javascript and Node.js.</para>

    <para>HTML5 is allowing custom elements and CSS classes can be defined for
    them. To avoid name conflicts, XForms elements are transformed into
    <tag>xforms-*</tag> elements (<tag>xforms-input</tag>, for example) and
    XForms attributes into <computeroutput>xf-*</computeroutput> attributes
    (<computeroutput>xf-selected</computeroutput>, for example). Shadow DOM is
    not currently used in XSLTForms but it cannot be used for grouping
    controls anyway.</para>

    <para>Each HTML attribute with AVT is renamed with the prefix
    <computeroutput>xf-template-</computeroutput> and the <computeroutput>xf-avt</computeroutput> attribute is added to the corresponding
    HTML element.</para>

    <para>XForms repeat elements are automatically converted into XForms
    repeat attributes when in HTML tables.</para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:input ref="PersonGivenName" incremental="true">
 <xf:label>Please enter your first name: </xf:label>
</xf:input>]]></programlisting>

    <para>Becomes</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xforms-input xf-ref="PersonGivenName" xf-incremental="true">
 <xforms-label>Please enter your first name: </xforms-label>
</xforms-input>]]></programlisting>

    <para>There is no Javascript instructions generation in the new XSLT
    stylesheet.</para>

    <para>HTML5 is not allowing custom elements within <tag>HEAD</tag> element so
    <tag>xforms-model</tag> elements have to go within <tag>BODY</tag> element.</para>

    <para>Inline XML instances and XML schemas have to be protected within
    <tag>SCRIPT</tag> elements with a not-supported type (<computeroutput>application/xml</computeroutput>, for example)
    to preserve letter cases. Because of a design error in Mozilla Firefox
    XSLT engine, instances are also to be serialized with entities.</para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:instance>
 <data xmlns="">
  <PersonGivenName/>
 </data>
</xf:instance>]]></programlisting>

    <para>Becomes</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xforms-instance>
 <script type="application/xml">&lt;data xmlns=""&gt;&lt;PersonGivenName/&gt;&lt;/data&gt;</script>
</xforms-instance>]]></programlisting>

    <para>As a consequence, for XSLTForms, the XSLT 1.0 stylesheet is lighter
    and the transformation is more than 3 times faster which is nicer for
    users, reducing the blank page wait.</para>

    <para>The XSLT stylesheet is much simpler and it becomes easy to rewrite
    it in a procedural programming language. It could also be done with
    XQuery <citation>XQuery</citation> <citation>XPF</citation>, of course.
    It has, actually, already been done in Javascript for
    Node.js because browser debuggers didn’t allow anymore breakpoints in
    Javascript when resulting from an XSLT transformation (it has been fixed
    in browsers since, but a few months later).</para>

    <para>It is also possible to directly write forms in HTML5 as the XSLT
    stylesheet would generate them. When generating XForms pages with XQuery
    at server side, it might be more convenient than finding some trick to add
    the XSLT processing instruction to be applied at client side not at
    server-side. It is, of course, also good for performance and there is no
    blank page effect at all.</para>

    <para>Yet, XSLTForms requires more custom sub elements, such as
    <tag>xforms-body</tag>, <tag>xforms-help</tag>, … to render XForms controls with HTML and
    CSS. This is now performed with Javascript when building the form.</para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xforms-input xf-ref="PersonGivenName" xf-incremental="true">
  <xforms-label>Please enter your first name: </xforms-label>
  </xforms-input>]]></programlisting>

    <para>Becomes</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xforms-input xf-ref="PersonGivenName" xf-incremental="true">
  <xforms-label>Please enter your first name: </xforms-label>
  <xforms-body>
    <input>
  </xforms-body>
  <xforms-required></xforms-required>
  <xforms-alert-mark></xforms-alert-mark>
  <xforms-alert></xforms-alert>
</xforms-input>]]></programlisting>

    <para>Because of CSS attribute selectors, CSS rules are powerful enough to
    manage custom elements visibility. XSLTForms is not anymore adding its own
    CSS classes: it is adding run-time attributes instead. For example, an
    XForms group without a binding will always be visible but, with a binding,
    an extra attribute (<computeroutput>xf-bound</computeroutput>) will be programmatically added when
    effectively bound to enable visibility. Models and actions are always
    hidden.</para>

    <para>Default CSS rules have been aligned to CSS rendering of XForms
    tutorial written by Steven Pemberton <citation>XFTUT</citation>.</para>

    <para>The <filename>xsltforms.css</filename> file has, effectively, been fully
    rewritten.</para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting language="css"><![CDATA[xforms-input:not([xf-required])[xf-invalid] > xforms-label::after {
  content: "\2716";
  color: red;
}]]></programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>XQuery/XPath parser in Javascript</title>

    <para>XForms is evaluating most XPath expressions in forms repeatedly. So,
    it is much more efficient, especially in browsers, to parse them once and
    preserve some compiled form for repeated evaluations.</para>

    <para>Previously, XSLTForms was using XSLT to parse XPath 1.0 expressions
    into Javascript code to create objects with a <code>.run()</code> method. Performance
    was good enough but with some unexpected delays for very long node names
    in XML instances…</para>

    <para>This XPath parser has been rewritten in Javascript to be executed
    just-in-time when an expression is to be evaluated for the first time.
    Again, the XSLT stylesheet is lighter and the blank page wait is
    reduced.</para>

    <para>Because the previous parser was targeting XPath 1.0, the new one has
    been extended to support XQuery 3.1 and generate XQueryX <citation>XQueryX</citation> stored in
    Javascript arrays (each element or attribute as an array of name and
    value).</para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[concat('Hello ', PersonGivenName, '. We hope you like XForms!')]]></programlisting>

    <para>Becomes</para>

    <programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[[Fleur.XQueryX.functionCallExpr,[
  [Fleur.XQueryX.functionName,['concat']],
  [Fleur.XQueryX.arguments,[
    [Fleur.XQueryX.stringConstantExpr,[[Fleur.XQueryX.value,['Hello ']]]],
    [Fleur.XQueryX.pathExpr,[
      [Fleur.XQueryX.stepExpr,[
        [Fleur.XQueryX.xpathAxis,['child']],
        [Fleur.XQueryX.nameTest,['PersonGivenName']]
      ]]
    ]],
    [Fleur.XQueryX.stringConstantExpr,[[Fleur.XQueryX.value,['. We hope you like XForms!']]]]
  ]]
]]]]></programlisting>

    <para>Which can be serialized in XQueryX as</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xqx:functionCallExpr>
  <xqx:functionName>concat</xqx:functionName>
  <xqx:arguments>
    <xqx:stringConstantExpr>
      <xqx:value>Hello </xqx:value>
    </xqx:stringConstantExpr>
    <xqx:pathExpr>
      <xqx:stepExpr>
        <xqx:xpathAxis>child</xqx:xpathAxis>
        <xqx:nameTest>PersonGivenName</xqx:nameTest>
      </xqx:stepExpr>
    </xqx:pathExpr>
    <xqx:stringConstantExpr>
      <xqx:value>. We hope you like XForms!</xqx:value>
    </xqx:stringConstantExpr>
  </xqx:arguments>
</xqx:functionCallExpr>]]></programlisting>

    <para>On Node.js, the XQueryX structure is, then, the input for a new
    XQuery engine, named Fleur <citation>Fleur</citation>, which also includes a DOM3 engine. It has to
    run asynchronous calls on functions such as <code>fn:doc()</code>, <code>http:send-request()</code>,
    <code>file:write()</code>, <code>prof:sleep()</code>,…</para>

    <para>Because <code>async</code>/<code>await</code> feature was not yet being supported in Node.js and
    old browsers, current version Fleur is still struggling with callbacks hell,
    call stack overflow. Using this version from XSLTForms would have needed a
    massive reorganization of sources: a converter from XQueryX to old XPath
    1.0 objects of XSLTForms has, temporarily, been added to remove the
    previous XPath 1.0 parser written in XSLT 1.0.</para>

    <para>The <code>fleur()</code> Javascript function has been added to be used within the
    Console in the browser debugger to evaluate XPath expressions.</para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[fleur("instance()")]]></programlisting>

    <para>Returns</para>

    <programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA["<data xmlns=\"\"><PersonGivenName/></data>"]]></programlisting>

    <para>Because rendering in Javascript console is rather limited, an XForms
    console has been created (accessible with F1 key). Currently limited to
    expression evaluation, it will be enriched to render, with HTML, Model
    Item Properties (<computeroutput>type</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>relevant</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>required</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>valid</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>read-only</computeroutput>,...) bound to
    XForms instance data nodes.</para>

    <para>With Node.js easily allowing to run an http server, Fleur is also a
    nice XQuery Web server for XSLTForms to generate inline XML instances,
    manipulate files, REST APIs,…</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>XQueryX 3.1 to Javascript transpiler</title>

    <para>Now, all browsers support async/await feature, so does Node.js. The
    Javascript arrays resulting from the XPath/XQuery parser can now be
    converted into Javascript functions.</para>

    <para>To evaluate an expression, the context is passed as unique parameter
    to the Javascript function. Its body contains a sequence of instructions
    with a Reverse Polish Notation order: arguments and parameters are stacked
    before function calls. Path evaluations require <code>if</code> statements to stop
    when a step returns an empty sequence. Predicates are performed with
    inline functions to be called for each sequence item. Error management is
    implemented throwing Javascript exceptions.</para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[concat('Hello ', PersonGivenName, '. We hope you like XForms!')]]></programlisting>

    <para>Becomes</para>

    <programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[ctx => {
  ctx.xqx_stringConstantExpr('Hello ');
  ctx.xqx_pathExpr();
  ctx.xqx_xpathAxis_child();
  ctx.xqx_nameTest("PersonGivenName");
  ctx.restoreContext();
  ctx.xs_string_1();
  ctx.xqx_stringConstantExpr('. We hope you like XForms!');
  ctx.fn_concat(3);
  return ctx;
};]]></programlisting>

    <para>This is optimized for Javascript interpreter own call stack and
    <code>async</code>/<code>await</code> use is reduced to minimal.</para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[doc('r2d2.urdf.xml')/robot/joint[@name eq 'swivel']]]></programlisting>

    <para>Becomes</para>

    <programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[async ctx => {
  ctx.xqx_pathExpr();
  await ctx.xqx_filterExpr_async(async ctx => {
    ctx.xqx_stringConstantExpr('r2d2.urdf.xml');
    await ctx.fn_doc_1_async();
    return ctx;
  });
  if (ctx.item.isNotEmpty()) {
    ctx.xqx_xpathAxis_child();
    ctx.xqx_nameTest("robot");
    if (ctx.item.isNotEmpty()) {
      ctx.xqx_xpathAxis_child();
      ctx.xqx_nameTest("joint");
      if (ctx.item.isNotEmpty()) {
        ctx.xqx_predicateExpr(ctx => {
          ctx.xqx_pathExpr();
          ctx.xqx_xpathAxis_attribute();
          ctx.xqx_nameTest("name");
          ctx.restoreContext();
          ctx.atomize();
          ctx.xqx_stringConstantExpr('swivel');
          ctx.xqx_valueComp(Fleur.eqOp);
          return ctx;
        });
      }
    }
  }
  ctx.restoreContext();
  return ctx;
};]]></programlisting>

    <para>It is also enabling static optimization when generating the
    Javascript source. For example, atomizing and node sorting are not always
    necessary when calling a function. Instead of Javascript, with XSLT, a
    more sophisticated transpiler could be written to transform XQueryX to
    Javascript functions.</para>

    <para>The <code>fleur()</code> Javascript function returns a type-explicit
    serialization which simulates an equivalent XQuery expression for the
    result of evaluation (more explicit than adaptative output).</para>

    <para>For example,</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[fleur("xs:date('2021-05-21') - xs:date('2021-05-10')")]]></programlisting>

    <para>Returns</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA["xs:dayTimeDuration('P11D')"]]></programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>XForms 2.0 support in XSLTForms</title>

    <para>XForms 2.0 comes with XPath 2.0 and later support. XSLTForms will
    have XPath 3.1 soon…</para>

    <para>XSLTForms is already supporting some major XForms 2.0 new features
    such as variables and AVT.</para>

    <para>XForms 2.0 Test Suite can be checked with XSLTForms running
    it. As for XForms 1.1 Test Suite, the corresponding form will be extended
    to produce the new Test Report.</para>

    <para>New extensions will also be considered such as the use of HTML5
    <tag>TEMPLATE</tag> elements to populate <tag>xforms-body</tag> elements, or the ability to
    script XForms actions and use XQuery Update Facility <citation>XQUF</citation> when applicable.</para>
  </section>

  <bibliography xml:id="references">

    <bibliomixed>
      <abbrev>XSLTForms</abbrev>
      Couthures, Alain: <title>XSLTForms</title>.<bibliomisc><link xl:href="https://github.com/AlainCouthures/declarative4all/tree/master/public/direct"/></bibliomisc>
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed>
      <abbrev>Fleur</abbrev>
      Couthures, Alain: <title>Fleur</title>.<bibliomisc><link xl:href="https://github.com/AlainCouthures/declarative4all/blob/master/build/js/fleur.js"/></bibliomisc>
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed>
      <abbrev>XQuery</abbrev>
      Robie, Jonathan - 
      Dyck, Michael (eds.): <title>XQuery 3.1: An XML Query Language</title>. W3C, 2017<bibliomisc><link xl:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery-31/"/></bibliomisc>
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed>
      <abbrev>XPF</abbrev>
      Kay, Michael (ed.): <title>XPath and XQuery functions and operators 3.1</title>. W3C, 2017<bibliomisc><link xl:href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xpath-functions-31/"/></bibliomisc>
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed>
      <abbrev>XQUF</abbrev>
      Snelson, John -
      Melton, Jim (eds.): <title>XQuery Update Facility 3.0</title>. W3C, 2015<bibliomisc><link xl:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery-update-30/"/></bibliomisc>
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed>
      <abbrev>XQueryX</abbrev>
      Melton, Jim - 
      Spiegel, Josh (eds.): <title>XQueryX 3.1</title>. W3C, 2017<bibliomisc><link xl:href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xquery-31/"/></bibliomisc>
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed>
      <abbrev>XF11</abbrev>
      Boyer, John M. (ed.): <title>XForms 1.1</title>. W3C, 2009<bibliomisc><link xl:href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2009/REC-xforms-20091020/"/></bibliomisc>
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed>
      <abbrev>XF2</abbrev>
      Bruchez, Eric - al. (eds.): <title>XForms
      2.0</title>. W3C, 2018<bibliomisc><link xl:href="https://www.w3.org/community/xformsusers/wiki/XForms_2.0"/></bibliomisc>
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed>
      <abbrev>XFTUT</abbrev>
      Pemberton, Steven: <title>XForms Hands On Tutorial</title>. 2020<bibliomisc><link xl:href="https://homepages.cwi.nl/~steven/xforms/xforms-hands-on/tutorial.xhtml"/></bibliomisc>
    </bibliomixed>
  </bibliography>
</article>