<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="resources/css/paper.css"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
	<info>
		<title>Dispelling Myths About Markup Formats: When What Why Where</title>
		<author>
			<personname>Liam Quin</personname>
			<email>liam@fromoldbooks.org</email>
			<uri>https://www.delightfulcomputing.com/</uri>
			<personblurb>
				<para><?oxy-placeholder content="Details about you"?></para>
			</personblurb>
			<affiliation>
				<jobtitle>Owner and coffee-slave</jobtitle>
				<orgname>Delightful Computing</orgname>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>declarative markup</keyword>
			<keyword>markup</keyword>
			<keyword>vocabulary</keyword>
			<keyword>markdown</keyword>
			<keyword>XML</keyword>
		</keywordset>
		<abstract>
			<para>Misunderstandings about the goals and strengths of different document and data interchange
				formats can lead to suboptimal decisions. Such misunderstandings appear widespread.
				The purpose of this paper is to suggest areas in which each format has strengths,
				and to provide clear explanations that people can use to place XML in the context of
				other current markup systems.</para>
			<para>Common misconceptions about XML include statements such as “XML was designed for Web
				services and therefore unsuitable for documents;” “XML was designed to replace HTML
				and has failed;” “XML cannot transmit semantics of any kind;” “XML is dead.” In
				fact, XML is alive and well. There are misconceptions about other formats, too, of
				course.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>Declarative markup languages have been around for many years. There were declarative
			systems built from Unix <emphasis>troff</emphasis> macro libraries in the 1970s and
			1980s, and of course SGML, Scribe, LaTeX and many others attempt to be more or less
			declarative and more or less general ways to represent and process documents with
			computers.</para>
		<para>The choice of which markup system to use should be based on clear well-understood
			criteria. These might include:<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Which notation has a closest fit to the document or documents. For
						example, a document with a lot of mixed markup and running text will be more
						difficult to process in some systems than others, as will a multilingual
						document;</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Which notation has associated tools that perform the processing the
						project needs;</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Which system the developers like the most or hate the most;</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Which system will be most likely to have active support for the entire
						duration of the project;</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>What will be the costs and what will be the gains of each format;</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>What are all the other similar projects using.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist></para>
		<para>Very often, the emotional aspects of the decision outweigh the technical
			aspects. This paper primarily explores the technical aspects, but
			also provides the reader with some ammunition to make an effective
			presentation in the emotional arena.</para>
		<para>The examples of criteria enumerated above do not include the
			single most important aspects of a decision: the context and the
			situation.  The <emphasis>context</emphasis> is an emergent property
			of organizational culture, fashion, predicted usage, and much more;
			some of this is listed explicitly here and some not. The
				<emphasis>situation</emphasis>, or the circumstances around the
			decision, must be viewed in terms of the wider context: instructions
			for identifying radioactive material in a nuclear power plant might
			have to be understood for a hundred years or more; a financial
			transaction must be archived for a period determined by a legal
			statute of limitation; British laws are written on vellum and stored
			in a stone tower in some cases for a thousand years or more. But
			over the lifetime of the information the context in which it is used
			may change: a financial record might be read by corporate accounting
			staff or, later, by a government auditor.</para>
		<para>The available tools will vary, but the organization may have a
			legal need to make information available regardless of applications
			originally used to process it. Similarly, software applications,
			operating systems, even display and user interface hardware
			constraints, all change over time. But a bigger question is who
			determines the format: who determines what information is stored,
			and how, and how is it to be used. A document that is read by an
			application to configure user preferences is likely designed by a
			programmer; a transcription of a mediaeval manuscript is more likely
			to be represented in ways determined by the people working with the
			text itself rather than with any particular application.</para>
		<para>The following sections attempt to identify good and less
			successful contexts for different markup formats, and, again, to
			provide ways of describing these contexts.</para>
		<section>
			<title> HTML: The HyperText Markup Language (HTML).</title>
			<para>The first standardized version of HTML was described by a
				combination of prose and an SGML DTD.  In this sense, and one
				other (see XHTML later in this paper) HTML shares some ancestry
				with XML However, people working with XML and with HTML often
				have very different ways of looking at markup. The difference
				can be illustrated by the meaning of the word
					<quote>semantics</quote> in the respective communities. In
				the HTML world, it’s common to hear people to describe the
				meaning of an element in terms of what a Web browser does when
				it encounters the start and end tags. Although most browser
				developers no longer refer to start and end tags as separate
				commands, the idea remains that operational semantics, Web
				browser behaviour, is the primary focus of HTML design. Marking
				up in the sense of identifying the content of a document seems
				alien here: there’s no <emphasis>poem</emphasis> element, for
				example, and tie <emphasis>cite</emphasis> element has no
				standard way to identify the author of a quotation or to give a
				bibliographic reference.</para>
			<para>HTML offers some extensibility: one can use markup such
				as:</para>
			<programlisting>&lt;span class="volno"3&lt;/span></programlisting>
			<para>to indicate the issue number of a volume containing a journal
				within a bibliographic reference. As with <quote>plain
					XML</quote> there is no standard way to mark up a
				bibliography and one is actually more likely in practice to find
				simply</para>
			<programlisting>&lt;b>3&lt;/b></programlisting>
			<para>in practice, or, worse,</para>
			<programlisting>&lt;span class="cn506dw"3&lt;/span></programlisting>
			<para>inserted by a content management system, framework, or word
				processor conversion.</para>
			<para>IHTML 5 includes elements such as <emphasis>nav</emphasis> and
					<emphasis>main</emphasis>, but their goal is to help people
				and programs navigate round documents by identifying the
				functions of different parts, not to try and label the parts and
				have the browser automatically function appropriately.</para>
			<para>HTML, then, is strongest when the Web is the primary end
				output format. It should be mentioned that there are also
				products that support generating PDF for print from HTML and
				CSS, and that the EPUB 3 standard uses XHTML (with a move to
				HTML possible in the future).</para>
			<para>A difficulty with HTML can be that the content can be
				difficult to reuse or re-purpose. If you do the work to annotate
				your HTML so that audiobooks can be made, or to use
					<emphasis>class</emphasis> attributes consistently enough
				that your aircraft repair manual can be generated automatically
				from your twenty-thousand-page operations manual, you will be
				replicating the work that might already have been done for you
				with an SGML or XML system: the tools are not generally designed
				for large, long, complex documents with precise domain-specific
				requirements. <emphasis role="bold">The primary application
					domain and usage context of HTML is the Webb
					browser.</emphasis></para>
			<para>A <emphasis>benefit</emphasis> of using HTML, however, can be
				reduced staff training. If your writers are already familiar
				with HTML, they can be up and running quickly. Beware, however,
				that saving a few hours of training does not end up costing you
				weeks or months of work when you discover the files are not
				consistently marked up or contain errors that weren’t flagged by
				(error-tolerant) HTML systems or Web browsers.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Markdown</title>
		<para>The name <emphasis>Markdown</emphasis> is of course a play on
				<emphasis>markup</emphasis>, with the implication that it’s
			somehow <emphasis>less</emphasis>: less work, not to hard to
			understand. For very simple documents Markdown can indeed be easy.
			In the manner of DEC NotesFiles from the 1970s and 1980s, one uses
			ASCII symbols for *bold* and _italic_. Hypertext links are more
			complex, and tables are supported only in some of the Markdown
			variants and can be a nightmare to use in a text editor.  <emphasis
				role="bold">The primary context for using markup is where people
				edit the text directly in a plain text editor</emphasis> and
			this means that it is really only intended, and only suitable for,
			simple documents. If you are using a tool that edits Markdown and
			hides the syntax then you might as well be editing HTML or XML: the
			primary reason to use Markdown files is that you have tools, such as
			github or a wiki of some sort, that consume it.</para>
		<para>Since there are no special tools needed, and since Markdown can
			really only cope with simple documents, the syntax can be easy to
			learn and training costs can be low. Markdown is generally close to
			a subset of the format used by Wikipedia, so, with extensions as
			needed, it can clearly scale. </para>
		<para>The semantics recorded in Markdown is purely operational: go bold,
			go italic; whilst some variants have additional tagging support, the
			primary assumption is that the appearance of the document (or the
			sound, when read out loud by text to speech) is primary.</para>
		<para>Markup is <emphasis>fabulous</emphasis>, though, for very simple
			README documents for projects such as computer source code, where
			the file can be read easily in a plain text viewer or editor without
			any special tools.</para>
		<para>If you choose to use Markdown for a project, be aware there are
			competing versions and make sure you have a fully compatible
			tool-set if you need one. If, however, you have figures, tables,
			footnotes, cross-references, running page headers (or even page
			numbers), or other features that go outside the normal remit of
			Markdown, or if you foresee a need to reuse the information and
			extract information from the text, you will almost certainly be
			better off with a richer format.</para>
		<para>If necessary, you can provide a tool to read a specific version of
			Markdown and convert it to (say) XML-encoded TEI documents for users
			in a text-based environment.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>RDF and Linked Data</title>
		<para>The Resource Description Framework (RDF) is really a data model for
			exchange of knowledge representation. Linked Data conforms to the
			same model: triplets of (subject, relationship, object), where all
			three terms are URIs (Uniform Resource Identifiers), so that if two
			triplets use the same URI for the same subject then the properties
			from both triples apply to it, and so on.</para>
		<para>RDF is <emphasis>not</emphasis> a model for documents. One can
			extract triplets from documents, but if it is to be useful the
			extraction is normally lossy: a list of the characters and places
			mentioned in a novel such as <citetitle>Star Wars</citetitle> is a
			common example, together with externally-derived triplets describing
			relationships such as <emphasis>was born at</emphasis> or
				<emphasis>loves</emphasis> or <emphasis>caused to become
				frozen</emphasis>. The list does not include every occurrence of
			every word in the novel, and the book cannot be reconstructed from
			the list. This example is very typical in its relationship to
			information, to the original book. Query languages such as GraphQL
			and SPARQL can then be used to explore the data and to support
			applications. Note that Linked Data may in many cases represent a
			complete data set, but even there the data is normally unordered,
			unlike words and paragraphs in writing.</para>
		<para>A weakness of RDF is that triplets are not natively labeled as to
			their source. In practice a <emphasis>triple store</emphasis> (a
			content management system for RDF) will normally extend the model to
			add permissions and information about who added each triple, but
			this is not normally accessible to the standard query languages. RDF
			stores may also support federated queries, in which case the
			additional information is not passed between systems, potentially
			leading to trust and security issues.</para>
		<para>The RDF model is also used for the Really Simple Syndication
			format (RSS), so that RSS files are simple XML representations of an
			RDF data model.</para>
		<para>RDF values are simple (atomic) strings: there is no direct support
			for mixed content such as running text in HTML, and text fragments
			containing element markup, such as one finds in RSS, have to be
			escaped and are treated by RDF systems as simple strings. RDF query
			languages tend to be weak in string processing, exacerbating
			difficulties here: you can’t generally use SPARQL to find all RSS
			feed items containing an HTML link to a given resource, for
			example.</para>
		<para>Linked Data in all of its forms provides ways to think about
			property-based reasoning, and can be very useful when working with
			metadata, especially in conjunction with other document formats. </para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>JavaScript Object Notation (JSON)</title>
		<para>JSON rapidly became very popular in the realm of Web development.
			It uses a mixture of <emphasis>array</emphasis>, which are ordered
			sequences of JSON items; <emphasis>objects</emphasis>, which are
			unordered collections of key-value pairs in which the key is a
			string and the value is any JSON item,;and, finally, values such as
			integers and strings. This is sufficient to represent static
			JavaScript objects (there are no function items).</para>
		<para>JSON has taken over from XML for the purpose of exchanging
			program-generated data via distributed APIs (largely replacing the
			use of SOAP) and for configuration of Web-based software. The
			notation uses square brackets for arrays and curly braces for
			objects, making it familiar to programmers of C-like languages and
			also allowing automatic brace-matching in many widely-used text
			editors.</para>
		<para>Large JSON files can be difficult to edit directly, as you can end
			up with large numbers of closing braces in a clump, reminiscent of
			LISP. It’s slightly easier than HTML in this regard, though, where
			you can end up with masses of <emphasis>&lt;/div></emphasis> tags
			together, given that text editors tend not to support tag-matching
			(show me the start tag corresponding to this close tag) but do
			support brace-matching.</para>
		<para>JSON does <emphasis>not</emphasis> support mixed content: that is,
			you can’t have running text with embedded markup. You can
				<emphasis>represent</emphasis> mixed content with an array of
			mixed strings and objects, but is not suitable for manipulation
			without tools or programs, and is considerably more verbose than the
			corresponding Markdown or even XML or HTML markup in this case. It’s
			also easy to lose significant spaces around the embedded markup when
			working in this fashion.</para>
		<para>There are libraries to import JSON files, and often to export
			them, in all major programming languages today. Often, reading JSON
			results in language-native objects, so that no query language is
			needed in simple cases.  This is a marked contrast from XML or HTML,
			where the result is usually a relatively complex data
			structure.</para>
		<para>JSON, then, is strongly favoured by many developers over any of
			the other formats in this paper because it is much easier for them.
			JSON belongs in a context in which the format of the data, the exact
			representation of information, and even the choice of what is to be
			represented is in the hands of programmers. In contexts in which
			document authors own their data and choose the contents, or where
			interoperability of the information between applications is
			paramount, JSON is much weaker than XML or RDF. However, see the
			next section for JSON and RDF.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>JSON-LD: JSON meets RDF</title>
		<para>JSON-LD is a way to represent linked data in JSON. It provides a
			mechanism to reduce the verbosity of the result by a
				<emphasis>context</emphasis> that authors can use to give short
			names for URIs in the data.</para>
		<para>JSON-LD is intended for environments and contexts (in the sense of
			this paper) in which JSON is already in use and there’s a need to
			add support for linked data using the RDF data model, perhaps to
			support graph-based query languages.</para>
		<para>Although JSON-LD combines the advantages of both JSON and RDF, it
			also inherits many of their disadvantages: the underlying data model
			of RDF is not extended to include the source of triplets, and mixed
			content is still not directly supported.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Portable Document Format (PDF)</title>
		<para>A disadvantage in some applications of all of the above formats is
			that they are not easily printed in a useful way. HTML is the
			closest, as Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) can be used with formatting
			software to make print-ready pages, but it is necessary to write
			separate CSS stylesheets for different HTML documents. The result of
			formatting HTML for print is usually PDF, which raises the question
			of whether PDF is useful as a document interchange format.</para>
		<para>PDF documents can be printed: PDF is a <emphasis>page description
				language</emphasis> and a PDF file describes the exact location
			of the page of everything inside it, both text and graphics.
			Unfortunately for document interchange this also means that PDF
			files cannot be edited to insert or delete content: the remainder of
			text on the page does not normally reflow.</para>
		<para>The PDF format contains machinery for embedding fonts, and for
			complex graphics. It is a compressed form of the PostScript
			language. Using PDF can provide <emphasis>page fidelity</emphasis>
			in many cases, in the sense that printed pages will look the same
			everywhere, scaled if desired to print on differently-sized
			paper.</para>
		<para>Since PDF is not easily edited, and has limited accessibility to
			people who are blind or who cannot distinguish certain colours or
			who need low (or high) contrast, it is not suitable as a primary
			document format.</para>
		<para>Reading and processing PDF in programs is difficult; there
				<emphasis>are</emphasis> libraries for C and JavaScript and
			other languages, but the resulting data structures are complex.
			There are no standard query languages for PDF, and it should be
			noted that even determining natural-language word-breaks is
			unreliable, using heuristics based on the position of each letter of
			the word on the page to try and detect the spaces. In addition, it
			is not usually possible to distinguish between a line-break at a
			hyphen in the original input and a hyphen inserted to facilitate
			line-breaking: text formatting is <emphasis>lossy</emphasis> so that
			the original document cannot be reconstructed reliably.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Domain-specific XML Vocabularies</title>
		<para>Like RDF, XML is really a framework for one’s own information: it
			does not come with much in the way of predefined semantics, whether
			behavioural or extrinsic. Like HTML, XML has a simple tag-based
			syntax for representing elements, but unlike HTML, XML does not
			predefine any element names. There is also no single data model for
			XML, although a few data models predominate in practice, primarily
			DOM and XDM.</para>
		<para>Since XML does not predefine element names, and also does not
			support anonymous (unnamed) elements, one needs a set of XML names
			for elements (and their attributes) to use. A set of element names
			and constraints on them can loosely be called a
				<emphasis>vocabulary</emphasis>. To make XML useful, there are
			three common paths people take, depending on their situation and the
			project context: to use a domain-specific XML vocabulary; to extend
			an existing XML vocabulary; to develop a custom XML vocabulary.
			Subsequent sections will describe each of these in turn, including
			some examples and some exceptions.</para>
		<para>Some frequently-heard complaints about XML should be mentioned
			here. People say that XML files are large compared to, for example,
			JSON; this is often true although XML compresses well. But the names
			repeated in XML end tags and the quotes around attribute values also
			provide a level of redundancy: experience with SGML minimization
			showed that the ability to omit these increased support costs
			considerably, because they created common situations in which the
			document would parse and even validate, but the interpretation of
			the parser differed from that of the human user.</para>
		<para>Another common complaint about XML from developers is that the
			APIs for working with XML are inelegant. Although this was true
			fifteen years ago, today there are often much more convenient APIs,
			ranging from XQuery and XPath to JQuery. But in any case the primary
			question of context for an XML project is whether the document
			maintainers are in control of the markup or whether the developers
			are. The former case is a primary use-case for XML. When developers
			are in control, JSON may be a better fit for short-form key-value or
			object-like documents. XML remains the format of choice for mixed
			content, where there is a mixture of text and markup at the same
			level.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>XHTML™: The Extensible HyperText Markup Language</title>
		<para>XHTML is a widely-used XML vocabulary that is also a reworking of
			HTML into XML. There are two primary versions:
				1.<emphasis>x</emphasis> and 5. Version 5 is the current
			version, and is an XML syntax for HTML 5. The original XHTML 1
			versions supported customization using XML DTDs, the original
			mechanism to define an XML vocabulary. XHTML 5 does not use
			grammar-based validation, and is primarily intended for use in Web
			browsers.  XHTML is also used by the EPUB standard for electronic
			books, where it has the advantage that a device-specific rendering
			engine can be used without having to worry about full HTML
			compatibility. This is important because Web browsers tend to be
			very flexible in displaying files containing errors, so existing
			content often contains a lot of syntax errors, which in turn means
			any software that tries to process arbitrary HTML needs a relatively
			complex parser and a lot of compatibility code. With XHTML, the
			syntax checking is strict, and enforced by the XML parser.</para>
		<para>Since XHTML files can be read by XML parsers, they are amenable to
			processing with XSLT and XProc, and to being stored in databases and
			queries with XQuery. Modern versions of XSLT and XQuery can also
			create XHTML 5 files.</para>
		<para>XHTML, like HTML, is designed in the context of Web browsers. Like
			all software, Web browsers evolve. Over time, elements change
			meaning or are dropped entirely. However, HTML 5 dropped the idea of
			including a version number in HTML files, which may cause problems
			with long-term archiving. Of course, any vocabulary could change
			over time, but the mitigation there is to combine grammar-based
			validation and specific version marking; HTML and XHTML do
			neither.</para>
		<para>XHTML is good for projects at the edge of XML and the Web, because
			they are equally usable by both tool-sets. The element names are
			also understood by Web search engines, so that serving XHTML files
			directly on the open Web makes sense and works. XHTML 5 is a good
			choice for generic documents such as blogs, as well as for Web-based
			applications. It has deficiencies in validation compared to
			domain-specific vocabularies, but it would also be fair to consider
			XHTML to be a domain-specific XML vocabulary for sharing documents
			on the World Wide Web. The name (X)HTML is sometimes used to refer
			to the vocabulary independently of whether the XML or slightly
			different HTML syntax is used.</para>
		<para>If you are producing your own domain-specific vocabulary, it is
			worth considering using (X)HTML 5 element names for plain text
			paragraphs and for markup within them, simply because (X)HTML is,
			overall, the most widely-used vocabulary on the planet. However,
			beware of false promises: if you use <emphasis>p</emphasis> for
			paragraphs, people may expect to be able to use
				<emphasis>ol</emphasis> for a list, <emphasis>i</emphasis> for
			italics, and so on.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>DocBook</title>
		<para>DocBook is a domain-specific XML vocabulary widely used for
			technical documentation.  There are widely-available tools to
			convert documents between DocBook and a wide variety of other
			formats, including ODF (q.v.) and into PDF.</para>
		<para>DocBook is a fairly large vocabulary, and uses the <quote>element
				pool</quote> concept described by Eve Maler and  Jeanne El
			Andaloussi in <citetitle>Developing SGML DTDs</citetitle> to make
			authoring easier: a core set of element names are available pretty
			much everywhere.</para>
		<para>Sometimes people criticize DocBook because the most common
			conversion to HTML does not produce elegant pages, but that is not a
			feature of DocBook itself, and when the conversion goes well, people
			do not realize the original format was DocBook.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Customizing DocBook: Mallard</title>
		<para>DocBook from the beginning provided for extensions, using an SGML
			and XML DTD syntax to allow people to add their own elements and
			modules. But sometimes you want to <emphasis>reduce</emphasis>
			rather than <emphasis>extend</emphasis>.</para>
		<para>A difficulty for authors using DocBook can be that at any given
			point in a document there can be a bewilderingly large number of
			possible elements that can be inserted. People working with DocBook
			all day quickly learn them, but occasional users can find this to be
			a barrier. Mallard is a subset of DocBook that was devised for
			writing online help the GNOME project, and is an example of a
			customization. Mallard also has its own Markdown variant,
				<emphasis>Ducktype</emphasis>.  Mallard also adds semi-automatic
			linking between topics, so that some processing is required before
			the files are usable by DocBook tools, but that is not an issue in
			the context of online help for the GNOME desktop.</para>
		<para>Note: Although DocBook has its own extension mechanisms, Mallard
			ended up as a standalone system, and today uses elements from HTML
			such as <emphasis>p</emphasis> and <emphasis>em</emphasis> rather
			than <emphasis>para</emphasis> and <emphasis>emphasis</emphasis> of
			DocBook. Like many project-specific extensions, it evolved.</para>
		<para>Starting off with an industry-standard vocabulary and customizing
			it can considerably reduce the work needed to develop a format, but
			people within the project have to make a conscious decision about
			the value of having their documents conform to the original
			vocabulary.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>The Text Encoding Initiative (TEI)</title>
		<para>The Text Encoding Initiative is both an organization and an
			eponymous vocabulary and associated methodology for transcribing
			texts for the purpose of analysis, study, and the production of fac
			simile editions. It is widely used in the Digital Humanities.</para>
		<para>The TEI vocabulary was originally intended
				<emphasis>always</emphasis> to be customized to particular
			academic projects. However, a core subset, TEI Lite, became popular.
			The TEI Consortium provides an extension mechanism, One Document
			Does It All (ODD), which simplifies making a customization of TEI,
			and in particular one that includes and combines specific
				<quote>modules</quote> such as one for drama or one for
			transcribing natural-language dictionaries.</para>
		<para>The primary context for using TEI is academic text processing and
			study of texts. An advantage of using it in that context is the high
			level of expertise and availability of assistance from other
			academics, as well as tools </para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Open Document Format (ODF), OOXML</title>
		<para>Whereas PDF files are compressed binary extensions of the
			PostScript language which, when executed, produce page images, ODF
			and OOXML are XML representations, again binary and compressed but
			extractable as text. However, rather than specifying the position of
			items on the page, ODF and OOXML provide an XML-based representation
			of editable documents.</para>
		<para>Word processors generally are strong in their tools for commenting
			on documents and performing collaborative reviews. The model is that
			a reviewer sends an annotated copy of a document to the author, who
			then in turn reviews the comments and suggested changes; this model
			fits well with many social contexts of writing and working with
			documents.</para>
		<para>The ODF and OOXML formats were designed to serialize OpenOffice
			and Microsoft Word™ documents (respectively) to XML, and support
			document revision. Unlike PDF, ODF and OOXML documents are intended
			to be editable by the recipient, and text reflows.</para>
		<para>Unfortunately, the OOXML specification, despite being very large,
			is also incomplete. In addition, the XML is written in the
			word-processing implementation domain, not in the user’s problem
			domain. The XML is complex and relatively difficult to work with,
			although freely available libraries and XSLT transformations exist
			to work with them. Word processor formats tend not to nest
			structures very much: for example, list items tend to be considered
			as automatically-numbered paragraphs and not to be nested inside a
			containing list element. Points at which there had one been style
			changes or selection boundaries may also be retained in the markup,
			further complicating processing.</para>
		<para>Word processing files are not generally ideal for archiving or
			interchange except in specific contexts such as the need for review
			or specific print-based workflows. Generated HTML may also have
			accessibility problems, and unless users are systematic with the use
			of named styles there tends to be only weak semantic labeling. Word
			processors in many cases reduce the apparent cost of writing,
			because they make it seem easy. Unfortunately in a wider context
			this can merely result in increasing costs and complexity elsewhere
			in workflow processes when finer-grained control over markup and
			document features may be needed. In this regard, word processor
			files can be similar to HTML documents. In all cases final archived
			documents need to be saved in format that is independent of any
			particular version of any software.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Raster Images</title>
		<para>Although raster (bitmap) image formats such as TIFF, PNG, GIF
			,BMP, JPEG and so forth can be suitable for non-textual content,
			text inside such image formats is really just a picture of text: it
			cannot be searched or copied and pasted, and text readers are not
			able to speak it out loud.</para>
		<para>Note that JPEG images in particular use a
				<emphasis>lossy</emphasis> compression, which introduces
				<quote>artifacts</quote> that can be visible and can hinder
			optical character recognition or other reuse of the files.</para>
		<para>Document page-images are most often used in situations where
			digital versions of original documents are unavailable and paper
			copies have been scanned. For archival use it’s important to use an
			image format that is open and standard and that has as few
			interoperability problems as possible. PNG is better than TIFF in
			this regard, since TIFF files vary between platforms, but both are
			better than Windows BMP or PhotoShop PSD (proprietary) or JPEG
			(lossy).</para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Conclusion</title>
		<para>The purpose of this paper is to discuss some formats, both XML and
			non-XML, with a perspective of the contexts in which each format is
			appropriate. There is no single <quote>best</quote> format, and no
			single way to represent information digitally. Rather, the context
			in which information will be used determines the perspective from
			which a choice should be made.</para>

	</section>

	<bibliography xml:id="liam-references">
		<bibliomixed> <abbrev>DB5SPEC</abbrev> <author>
			<personname><surname>Walsh</surname><firstname>Norman</firstname></personname>
			</author>: <title>The DocBook Schema</title>. Working Draft 5.0a1, <date>29 June
			2005</date>, <orgname>OASIS</orgname>. <bibliomisc><link
			xl:href="http://www.docbook.org/specs/wd-docbook-docbook-5.0a1.html"/></bibliomisc> </bibliomixed>
		
		<bibliomixed>
			<abbrev>SGMLDTD</abbrev>
			<author>
				<personname><surname>Maler</surname>
					<firstname>Eve</firstname></personname>
			</author>, <author>
				<personname><surname>El
						Andaloussi</surname><firstname>Jeanne</firstname></personname>
			</author>: <title>Developing SGML DTDs</title>. <date>15 December
				1995</date>,<publishername>Prentice Hall PTR</publishername>
		</bibliomixed>
		
	</bibliography>

</article>
