<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Leveraging the Power of OpenAI and Schematron for Content Verification and
            Correction</title>
        <author>
            <personname><firstname>Octavian</firstname>
                <surname>Nadolu</surname></personname>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname>Oxygen XML Editor</orgname>
            </affiliation>
            <email>octavian_nadolu@oxygenxml.com</email>
        </author>
        <abstract>
            <para>The purpose of this presentation is to provide an overview of what AI is, the
                potential benefits of using AI with Schematron and SQF for content verification and
                correction, and some of the challenges we face when using AI for this purpose. </para>
            <para>AI (Artificial Intelligence) is a branch of computer science that studies and
                develops theories, methods, and technologies to allow machines to perceive,
                understand, and act in the world. AI is used to create algorithms that can learn,
                understand, and make decisions in complex environments. AI is used in many areas,
                including natural language processing, robotics, computer vision, data mining, and
                machine learning. </para>
            <para>OpenAI is a research laboratory dedicated to developing and deploying AI in order
                to solve complex problems. OpenAI has developed algorithms that use reinforcement
                learning and deep learning to solve problems in robotics, natural language
                processing, and computer vision. </para>
            <para>Schematron can be used to identify elements of a document and make assumptions
                about them, providing a powerful boost when used in conjunction with OpenAI
                algorithms. Using OpenAI algorithms with Schematron and SQF (Schematron Quick Fix)
                can help to automate the verification of the correctness, completeness, and accuracy
                of content. OpenAI algorithms can be used to automatically check and correct errors
                in content and markup. This can save time and money for content creators and
                publishers, as well as improving the accuracy of the content. </para>
            <para>However, there are challenges associated with using OpenAI for content
                verification and correction. OpenAI algorithms may not accurately identify errors in
                content, and may not be able to make corrections that are appropriate for the
                context. Additionally, OpenAI algorithms may not be able to detect errors that are
                due to cultural or regional differences in language.</para>
            <para>In conclusion, OpenAI can be a powerful tool for verifying and correcting content,
                but there are challenges associated with using OpenAI for this purpose. It is
                important to consider these challenges when using OpenAI for content verification
                and correction. </para>
        </abstract>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>In today's digital age, content verification and correction have become increasingly
            important, especially for businesses and organizations that rely on the accuracy and
            consistency of their content to communicate with their audiences. To address this need,
            many companies are turning to artificial intelligence (AI) and Schematron to automate
            the process of ensuring that their content meets certain standards and guidelines.
            Schematron, a powerful language for specifying rules for XML documents, allows
            developers to define their own custom messages and provide more descriptive feedback to
            users. By leveraging the power of AI and Schematron, businesses can streamline their
            content creation and editing processes and ensure that their messaging is clear,
            consistent, and error-free.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Artificial Intelligence</title>
        <para>Artificial Intelligence (AI) refers to the ability of machines to perform tasks that
            typically require human intelligence, such as visual perception, speech recognition,
            decision-making, and language translation. AI is a broad field that encompasses a range
            of techniques, including machine learning, deep learning, natural language processing,
            and computer vision.</para>
        <para>Machine learning is a subset of AI that involves training algorithms to learn patterns
            in data, without being explicitly programmed. Deep learning is a type of machine
            learning that uses neural networks with multiple layers to learn increasingly complex
            representations of data. Natural language processing is a subfield of AI that focuses on
            enabling machines to understand and generate human language. Computer vision is another
            subfield of AI that focuses on enabling machines to interpret and analyze visual
            information.</para>
        <para>AI has numerous real-world applications across various domains, including healthcare,
            finance, transportation, customer service, and entertainment. As technology advances, AI
            continues to evolve and has the potential to revolutionize industries and enhance
            various aspects of human life.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Generative Pre-trained Transformer(GPT)</title>
        <para>Generative Pre-trained Transformer (GPT) is a type of deep learning model that uses a
            transformer architecture to generate natural language text. The model is pre-trained on
            a large corpus of text data and then fine-tuned on specific tasks, such as language
            translation or text completion.</para>
        <para>The transformer architecture is a type of neural network that is designed to process
            sequential data, such as text. It uses self-attention mechanisms to capture the
            relationships between different parts of a sequence, allowing it to generate more
            coherent and contextually appropriate text.</para>
        <para>GPT is particularly useful for natural language processing tasks such as language
            translation, text summarization, and text completion. It has achieved state-of-the-art
            performance on a range of benchmarks, including the GLUE benchmark for natural language
            understanding and the COCO captioning challenge for image captioning.</para>
        <para>Overall, GPT represents a significant advance in the field of natural language
            processing, enabling more accurate and effective text generation and
            understanding.</para>
        <para>A transformer is a type of deep learning model architecture that is used for
            processing sequential data, such as natural language text. It was introduced in a 2017
            paper by Vaswani et al. and has since become a popular choice for a wide range of
            natural language processing tasks.</para>
        <para>The transformer architecture is based on the idea of self-attention, which allows the
            model to focus on different parts of the input sequence when making predictions. This is
            in contrast to traditional recurrent neural networks (RNNs), which process sequential
            data in a linear fashion and can struggle with long-term dependencies.</para>
        <para>The transformer consists of an encoder and a decoder, each of which contains multiple
            layers of self-attention and feedforward neural networks. The encoder processes the
            input sequence, while the decoder generates the output sequence. During training, the
            model learns to predict the next token in the sequence based on the previous tokens, and
            can be fine-tuned for specific tasks such as language translation or text
            classification.</para>
        <para>Overall, the transformer architecture has proven to be highly effective for natural
            language processing tasks, achieving state-of-the-art results on a range of
            benchmarks.</para>
        <para>Embeddings, in the context of natural language processing (NLP) and machine learning,
            refer to the mathematical representations of words, sentences, or documents in a
            continuous vector space. Embeddings are used to capture the semantic meaning and
            relationships between words, allowing machines to understand and process human
            language.</para>
        <para>Traditionally, words were represented as one-hot vectors, where each word in a
            vocabulary is assigned a unique binary vector with a dimension equal to the vocabulary
            size. However, one-hot vectors lack semantic information and are not suitable for
            machine learning algorithms that rely on numerical representations.</para>
        <para>Embeddings address this limitation by mapping words to dense, lower-dimensional
            vectors in a continuous space. The goal is to encode similar words with similar
            embeddings, such that their spatial proximity reflects their semantic similarity. This
            is achieved through unsupervised learning algorithms, such as Word2Vec, GloVe, or
            fastText, which learn embeddings based on the context in which words appear in large
            corpora.</para>
        <para>The resulting word embeddings can capture various linguistic relationships, such as
            word analogies (e.g., "king" - "man" + "woman" = "queen") and syntactic patterns.
            Additionally, word embeddings can be extended to represent larger units of text, such as
            sentences or documents, by aggregating the embeddings of constituent words.</para>
        <para>Embeddings have become a fundamental component of many NLP tasks, including language
            translation, sentiment analysis, information retrieval, and text classification. They
            enable machine learning models to leverage the semantic information encoded in text and
            make more accurate predictions or understandings based on it.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Schematron and AI</title>
        <para>Schematron is a schema language for XML documents that allows for more flexible and
            expressive validation than traditional XML schema languages like XML Schema and DTD.
            Schematron uses a rule-based approach to validation, allowing for complex business rules
            and constraints to be expressed in a clear and concise manner. It is often used in
            conjunction with other schema languages to provide more comprehensive validation of XML
            documents.</para>
        <para>Schematron can be used with AI to automatically verify documents using an AI model.
            This can be done by integrating the AI model into the Schematron rules to check for
            specific criteria. For example, the AI model can check for the use of active/passive
            voice in the document and the Schematron rules can be set up to flag any instances where
            the wrong voice is used. Similarly, the AI model can check for adherence to a specific
            style guide and the Schematron rules can be set up to flag any deviations from that
            guide. The AI model can also check if the document answers a specific question and the
            Schematron rules can be set up to flag any instances where the question is not answered.
            Additionally, the AI model can check for spelling and grammar errors and the Schematron
            rules can be set up to flag any errors found by the model. Overall, integrating AI with
            Schematron can help to automate the verification process and ensure that documents meet
            specific criteria.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Schematron Quick Fix and AI</title>
        <para>Schematron QuickFix (SQF) is a simple language that allows the Schematron developer to
            define actions that will correct the problems reported by Schematron rules. SQF was
            created as an extension of the Schematron language. It was developed within the W3C
            "Quick-Fix Support for XML Community Group". The first draft of the Schematron Quick Fix
            specification was published in April 2015, second draft in March 2018, and it is
            available on the <link xlink:href="https://www.w3.org/community/quickfix/">W3C Quick-Fix
                Support for XML community group</link> page.</para>
        <para>Schematron Quick Fix (SQF) can be used with AI to automatically correct problems in
            documents. Here are some steps to use SQF with AI:<orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Create a set of rules using Schematron to identify problems in the
                        document. These rules can include grammar and spelling checks, as well as
                        more complex checks like sentence structure and coherence.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Use AI algorithms to generate suggestions for how to fix the identified
                        problems. For example, an AI algorithm could suggest rephrasing a sentence
                        to use active voice or to have a certain word count.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Implement the suggested fixes using SQF. SQF allows for user-defined fixes
                        to be applied automatically, making it easy to correct problems in the
                        document without manual intervention.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Test the document to ensure that the fixes have been applied correctly and
                        that the document is now error-free.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist></para>
        <para>By combining Schematron, AI, and SQF, it is possible to automate the process of
            correcting problems in documents, saving time and improving the overall quality of the
            document.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Implementation of AI in Schematron</title>
        <para>To call an implementation of AI in Schematron, you can use XSLT functions or extension
            functions. </para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Using XSLT functions: </para>
                    <para>You can use XSLT functions to call an implementation of AI in Schematron.
                        For example, you can use implement function to call ChatGPT API. Here's an example:<example>
                            <title>Example of XSLT functions that calls ChatGPT</title>
                            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;xsl:function name="ai:chatGPT">
    &lt;xsl:param name="userInput"/>
    &lt;xsl:variable name="url" select="'https://api.chatgpt.com/v1/chatbot/question'"/>
    &lt;xsl:variable name="requestBody" select="concat('{', '&amp;quot;text&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;',
        $userInput,'&amp;quot;', '}')"/>
    &lt;xsl:variable name="response" select="document(concat($url, '?apiKey=',
        '&amp;lt;your_api_key>'))//response"/>
    &lt;xsl:sequence select="$response"/>
&lt;/xsl:function></programlisting>
                        </example></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Using extension functions:</para>
                    <para>You can also use extension functions to call an implementation of AI in
                        Schematron. For example, you can define an extension function called
                        `ai:verify-content` that takes an instruction and content as parameters and
                        returns a boolean. Here's an example: <example>
                            <title>Example an extensions function ai:verify-content()</title>
                            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sch:rule context="...">
  &lt;sch:assert test="ai:verify-content('instruction', 'content')">Message&lt;/sch:assert>
&lt;/sch:rule></programlisting>
                        </example></para>
                    <para>In this example, the `ai:verify-content` function is called within a
                        `sch:assert` element to verify that the content meets certain criteria
                        specified by the instruction.</para>
                    <para>To modify the content using AI, you can define an extension function
                        called `ai:transform-content` that takes an instruction and content as
                        string parameters and returns transformed content as string. You can use
                        this function an SQF action to correct the content. Here's an example: <example>
                            <title>Example an extension function ai:transform-content</title>
                            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sqf:fix id="rephrase">
    &lt;sqf:replace select="ai:transform-content('instruction', 'content')"/>
&lt;/sqf:fix></programlisting>
                            <para> The `ai:transform-content` function is called within a
                                `sqf:replace` element and will transform the given content according
                                to the instruction, the returned result will be inserted in the
                                document replacing the current node content .</para>
                        </example></para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Examples of AI-driven Schematron and SQF Solutions</title>
        <section>
            <title>Check text consistency</title><para>One use case for Schematron using AI is to check if the text in an XML document is
            consistent and easy to read and understand. For example, you may want to ensure that the
            text is written in plain language, uses simple sentence structures, and avoids technical
            jargon or complex terminology. To achieve this, you can define a Schematron rule that
            checks for specific patterns or structures in the text. For instance, you may define a
            rule that checks if the sentences are too long or if the text contains too many complex
            words or phrases. If the rule detects any issues, it can report an error or a warning to
            the user, indicating the specific location of the problem.</para>
        <para>
            <example>
                <title>Example a Schematron rule that verifies if the text is easy to read and
                    understand</title>
                <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sch:rule context="p">
    &lt;sch:assert test="ai:verify-content('Is the text easy to read and understand?', .)">
        The text in not easy to read and understand&lt;/sch:assert>
&lt;/sch:rule></programlisting>
            </example>
        </para>
        <para>Once you have identified the issues in the text, you can use SQF (Schematron Quick
            Fixes) to provide suggestions or corrections to the user. For example, you may provide a
            suggestion to correct the text to be easy to read and understand by calling the
            ai:transform-content() function.</para>
        <example>
            <title>SQF fix that corrects the text to be easy to read and understand</title>
            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sqf:fix id="rephrase">
    &lt;sqf:description>
        &lt;sqf:title>Correct the consistency of the text&lt;/sqf:title>
    &lt;/sqf:description>
    &lt;sqf:replace match="text()" select="ai:transform-content(
		'Correct the text to be easy to read and understand', .)"/>
&lt;/sqf:fix></programlisting>
        </example></section>
        <section>
            <title>Check text voice</title>
            <para>In this example, we want to create a rule that verifies if the text voice is
                active. This means that the text should be written in a way that emphasizes the
                subject of the sentence and uses active verbs. For example, instead of saying "The
                ball was thrown by John", we should say "John threw the ball". </para>
            <para>
                <example>
                    <title>Rule that verifies if the text voice is active</title>
                    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sch:rule context="shortdesc">
    &lt;sch:assert test="ai:verify-content('Is active voice used?', .)">
        In the description we should use active voice.&lt;/sch:assert>
&lt;/sch:rule></programlisting>
                </example>
            </para>
            <para>If the text does not follow this rule, we can create a fix that reformulates the
                text to use active voice. This will improve the clarity and readability of the text. </para>
            <example>
                <title>SQF fix that that reformulates the text to use active voice</title>
                <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sqf:fix id="rephrase">
    &lt;sqf:description>
        &lt;sqf:title>Reformulate the text to use active voice&lt;/sqf:title>
    &lt;/sqf:description>
    &lt;sqf:replace match="text()" select="ai:transform-content('
		Reformulate to use active voice', .)"/>
&lt;/sqf:fix></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Answer to question</title>
            <para>Another example is a rule that checks if the text answers to a specified question.
                Let's say we have a text that discusses OpenAI, but we want to make sure that the
                text actually answers the question "What is OpenAI?" </para>
            <para>
                <example>
                    <title>Rule that verifies if the text does answer to a specific question</title>
                    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sch:rule context="p[@id='openai']">
    &lt;sch:assert test="ai:verify-content('Does it answers to the question: What is OpenAI?', .)">
        The test does not answer to the question "What is OpenAPI?" &lt;/sch:assert>
&lt;/sch:rule></programlisting>
                </example>
            </para>
            <para>If the text passes this rule, we can be reasonably confident that it does answer
                the question "What is OpenAI?" </para>
            <para>However, if the text does not pass the rule, we know that it may not be providing
                a clear answer to the question. In this case, we might need to revise or restructure
                the text to make sure it does answer the question.  </para>
            <example>
                <title>SQF fix that that reformulates the text to answer to the question</title>
                <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sqf:fix id="rephrase">
    &lt;sqf:description>
        &lt;sqf:title>Reformulate the text to answer to the question: 
                        What is OpenAI?&lt;/sqf:title>
    &lt;/sqf:description>
    &lt;sqf:replace match="text()" select="ai:transform-content(
        'Reformulate the text to answer to the question: What is OpenAI?', .)"/>
&lt;/sqf:fix></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Check the number of words</title>
            <para>In this case, we want to create a rule that checks the number of words in the
                description element of an XML document. The rule should ensure that the description
                contains less than 50 words. If the description contains more than 50 words, the
                rule should fail and report an error. The implementation uses XPath functions to
                tokenize the string and count the words. </para>
            <para>
                <example>
                    <title>Rule that verifies the number of words from the shortdesc element</title>
                    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sch:rule context="shortdesc">
    &lt;sch:report test="count(tokenize(.,'\s+')) > 50">
         The description must contain less than 50 words.&lt;/sch:report>
&lt;/sch:rule></programlisting>
                </example>
            </para>
            <para>You can also provide a fix for the error by suggesting a corrected version of the
                description that contains less than 50 words. The AI can help you to do this by
                reformulating the phrase.</para>
            <example>
                <title>SQF fix that reformulates the phrase to have less than 50 words</title>
                <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sqf:fix id="rephrase">
    &lt;sqf:description>
        &lt;sqf:title>Reformulate phrase to contain less than 50 words&lt;/sqf:title>
    &lt;/sqf:description>
    &lt;sqf:replace match="text()" select="ai:transform-content(
           'Reformulate phrase to contain less than 50 words', .)"/>
&lt;/sqf:fix></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Check if  block of text should be a list</title>
            <para>This Schematron rule is designed to check if a block of text should be converted
                to a list. It can be used to ensure that content is properly formatted and
                structured for readability and accessibility.  </para>
            <para>
                <example>
                    <title>Rule that verifies the text from a paragraph should be converted to a
                        list</title>
                    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sch:rule context="p">
    &lt;sch:report test="contains(., '- ')">
        The text should be converted to a list&lt;/sch:report>
&lt;/sch:rule></programlisting>
                </example>
            </para>
            <para>If the rule detects that the text should be converted to a list, it can trigger a
                fix that generates an unordered or ordered list from the set of phrases. This can
                help to improve the organization and clarity of the content, making it easier for
                readers to understand and follow. </para>
            <example>
                <title>SQF fix that creates a list from a set of phrases</title>
                <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sqf:fix id="replace">
    &lt;sqf:description>
        &lt;sqf:title>Create a list from the phrases from the paragraph&lt;/sqf:title>
    &lt;/sqf:description>
    &lt;sqf:replace match="text()">
        &lt;xsl:value-of select="ai:transform-content(
            'Create a Dita unorderd list with an item from each phrase', .)"
            disable-output-escaping="yes"/>
    &lt;/sqf:replace>
&lt;/sqf:fix></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>If the generated content contains markup you need to use the
                    <emphasis>disable-output-escaping="yes"</emphasis> in order to insert the markup
                unescaped in the document.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>User-Entry - Check technical terms</title>
            <para>Technical terms are specialized words or phrases that are used within a particular
                field or industry. When writing technical documents, it's important to ensure that
                these terms are explained adequately so that readers who may not be familiar with
                them can understand the content. One way to check if technical terms are explained
                adequately is to use a Schematron rule that interrogates an AI . The rule might look
                something like this:  </para>
            <para>
                <example>
                    <title>Rule that verifies if the technical terms are explained adequately</title>
                    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sch:report test="ai:verify-content('Are the technical terms explained ambiguous?', .)"
       The text uses technical terms that are not explained adequately.&lt;/sch:report></programlisting>
                </example>
            </para>
            <para>To fix this issue, the user could provide an explanation for the technical term.
                However, sometimes it may be necessary to reformulate the phrase to make it more
                understandable. In this case, a fix could be added to the Schematron rule that
                allows the user to specify how to reformulate the phrase. </para>
            <example>
                <title>SQF fix that allows the user to specify the prompt that will be send to the
                    AI</title>
                <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sqf:fix id="reformulateUser">
    &lt;sqf:description>
        &lt;sqf:title>Specify how to reformulate the phrase&lt;/sqf:title>
    &lt;/sqf:description>
    &lt;sqf:user-entry name="userInput" default="'
         Reformulate phrase and replace the ambiguous terms with a more accurate one'">
        &lt;sqf:description>sqf:title>How to correct:&lt;/sqf:title>sqf:description>
    &lt;/sqf:user-entry>
    &lt;sqf:replace match="text()" select="ai:transform-content($userInput, .)"/>
&lt;/sqf:fix></programlisting>
            </example>
            <para>The user can specify the instruction for the fix in the sqf:user-entry. A default
                value instruction is proposed to the user, but the user can decide do correct the
                phrase providing other instruction to the AI system (such as: explain term, define
                term, replace term with a new one)</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Generate Fix Automatically</title>
        <para>When a Schematron rule fails during validation, it generates an error message
            indicating the context of the error. However, it does not provide a fix for the issue.
            The fix for the error message can be generated using AI, which analyzes the context of
            the rule and suggests a correction to the XML document. This can help to automate the
            process of fixing errors in XML documents and save time for developers.</para>
        <example>
            <title>Example: A Schematron rule that verifies the number of words from shortdesc
                element</title>
            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;sch:rule context="shortdesc">
    &lt;sch:report test="count(tokenize(.,'\s+')) > 50">
         The description must contain less than 50 words.&lt;/sch:report>
&lt;/sch:rule></programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>You can use the Schematron rule to generate a fix using AI. The content to correct is
            provided in the context of the Schematron rule, and the goal is to use AI to generate a
            new text that will serve as a fix for the issue. Specifically, the AI should generate a
            new text to replace the content of the "shortdesc" element, which should contain a brief
            description of the issue.</para>
        <para>This approach can be extended beyond Schematron to other types of error messages in
            software development. By using AI to generate fixes automatically, developers can save
            time and focus on more complex tasks, while also improving the overall quality of their
            code.</para>
        <para>Of course, there are some challenges to this approach. For example, the message needs
            to be as concise as possible so that the AI can use it effectively. Additionally,
            sometimes the context of the message may need to be modified or additional operations
            may need to be performed to generate an effective fix. However, overall this approach
            can save a lot of time and effort compared to manually creating</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Develop Schematron using AI</title>
        <para>Artificial intelligence can be used to develop Schematron rules. Machine learning
            algorithms can be trained to recognize these patterns and generate Schematron rules that
            can be used to validate future XML documents. </para>
        <para>The user can provide a prompt that describes the Schematron rule. He can describe a
            specific scenario or use case for which the Schematron rules will be created using AI.
            The AI will generate the rules based on the scenario he provides.</para>
        <para>For example the user can provide a prompt like: "A Schematron assert that verifies the
            number of words to be 10". The generated content by the AI can be something like
            this:<programlisting language="xml">&lt;sch:assert test="count(tokenize(., '\s+')) = 10">There should be exactly 10.&lt;/sch:assert></programlisting></para>
        <para>Another example of prompt can be to verify if the text contains an email. I this case
            the prompt can be something like: "A Schematron assert that verifies if there is an
            email in text". The content generated by the AI can be something like
            this:<programlisting language="xml">&lt;sch:assert test="matches(., '\b[A-Za-z0-9._%+-]+@[A-Za-z0-9.-]+\.[A-Z|a-z]{2,}\b')">
                There is no email in the text&lt;/sch:assert></programlisting></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>Schematron is an XML-based language used for validating the content of XML documents.
            It allows users to define rules that can be used to verify the correctness and
            completeness of the content. With the help of AI, Schematron can be made even more
            powerful.</para>
        <para>One way to use AI with Schematron is to use machine learning algorithms to analyze the
            content of XML documents and identify patterns and anomalies. This can help to detect
            errors and inconsistencies that might otherwise be missed by traditional validation
            techniques. For example, AI can be used to identify semantic errors, such as incorrect
            usage of terms or concepts, that might not be caught by simple syntactic
            validation.</para>
        <para>Another way to use AI with Schematron is to use SQF fixes to correct errors
            automatically. For example, if an XML document contains a misspelled word, an AI-powered
            Schematron can automatically correct the spelling without requiring any manual
            intervention. This can save time and effort and improve the accuracy of the validation
            process.</para>
        <para>In addition, AI can be used to generate fixes automatically. For example, if an XML
            document contains an error that can be corrected automatically, an AI-powered Schematron
            can generate the corrected version of the document automatically. This can save time and
            effort and improve the overall quality of the content.</para>
        <para>As AI technology continues to improve and evolve, Schematron can be further developed
            to take advantage of these advancements. For example, new machine learning algorithms
            can be integrated into Schematron to improve its ability to detect errors and anomalies. </para>
        <para>Overall, the use of AI with Schematron has the potential to revolutionize the way
            content is validated and corrected. By leveraging the power of AI, Schematron can
            provide more accurate and efficient validation, leading to higher quality content and
            improved user experiences. As AI technology continues to grow and improve, the
            possibilities for Schematron are endless.</para>
    </section>
</article>
