<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
  <info>
    <title>What’s in a Schematron?</title>
    <author>
      <personname>David Maus</personname>
      <email>dmaus@dmaus.name</email>
      <uri>https://dmaus.name</uri>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>State and University Library Hamburg</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Schematron</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <abstract>
      <para>This paper presents a preliminary classification of Schematron concepts and discusses
        the three most important topics covered by ISO Schematron: Rule based validation, schema
        composition, and reporting. It concludes with rough sketch of a new rule based validation
        language in the tradition of Schematron that takes the advantages in markup language
        technology into consideration.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Schematron is a rule based validation language for structured documents. It was designed
      by Rick Jelliffe in the late 1990s <citation>JELLIFFE1999</citation> and standardized as part
      of the ISO Document Schema Language Definitions (DSDL) family in 2006. The last non-ISO
      version was Schematron 1.6, published in 2002. <citation>JELLIFFE2002</citation> Since the
      standardization as ISO/IEC 19757-3 two editions have been published. The 2nd edition in 2016,
      the 3rd edition in 2020. The 3rd edition of ISO Schematron will most likely be the last: The
      working group was disbanded and, more importantly, ISO removed Schematron from the list of
      publicly available standards, effectively putting an end to ISO Schematron as an Open
      Standard.</para>
    <para>While losing an Open Standard is annoying it gives the opportunity to look at the
      specification as an object of an analytic inquiry. Rather than comparing Schematron with other
      schema languages we could look at ISO Schematron’s concepts and ask what function they serve
      or which topic they cover. This analytic perspective may help structuring a discussion of
      potential shortcomings or missed opportunities.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>A preliminary classification of Schematron concepts</title>
    <para><xref linkend="concepts"/> shows a first classification attempt and identifies six major
      topics in descending order of importance: Rule based validation, schema composition,
      reporting, documentation, pattern templating and instance document selection. In the following
      sections I will provide a brief summary of the topic and the associated concepts, and discuss
      shortcomings of the current specification.</para>
    <table xml:id="concepts">
      <info>
        <title>Classification of Schematron concepts</title>
      </info>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Topic</entry>
            <entry>Schematron concepts</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Rule based validation</entry>
            <entry>Assertion, Rule, Pattern, Schema, Query language </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Schema composition</entry>
            <entry>Abstract rule, Phase, Inclusion</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Reporting</entry>
            <entry>Natural language statement, Properties, Templating language</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Documentation</entry>
            <entry>Title, Paragraph, Reference to external documentation</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Pattern templating</entry>
            <entry>Abstract pattern</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Instance document selection</entry>
            <entry>Subordinate documents</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <section>
      <title>Rule based validation</title>

      <section>
        <title>Summary</title>
        <para>Rule based validation is at the core of Schematron. For Schematron, rule-based
          validation means that a document is considered to be valid if it passes a specified set of
          assertion tests.</para>
        <para>An <glossterm>assertion test</glossterm> is a boolean function over a set of nodes. It
          is associated with zero or more natural-language statements. Schematron uses two elements
          to represent assertions: An assertion expressed as a <tag class="element">sch:assert</tag>
          element succeeds if the assertion test evaluates to boolean true, an assertion expressed
          as <tag class="element">sch:report</tag> element succeeds if the assertion test evaluates
          to false. Both use a <tag class="attribute">test</tag> attribute for the assertion
          test.</para>
        <para>A <glossterm>rule</glossterm> is an unordered set of assertions. The assertion
          elements are grouped into a <tag class="element">sch:rule</tag> element with a <tag
            class="attribute">context</tag> attribute containing a <glossterm>context
            expression</glossterm>. The context expression is an expression that selects nodes from
          the instance document. A rule is said to "fire" if its context expression selects a
          non-empty set of nodes. All assertions of the rule are evaluated for each node of the set.
          A single assertion is checked by evaluating the assertion expression with the respective
          node as context. A rule validates a node if all assertions succeed.</para>
        <para>A <glossterm>pattern</glossterm> is an ordered set of rules. The lexical order of the
          rule elements in the Schematron document acts as an if-then-else switch for nodes of the
          instance document. A node is checked with at most one rule per pattern.</para>
        <para>A <glossterm>schema</glossterm> is an unordered set of patterns. The pattern elements
          are grouped into a <tag class="element">sch:schema</tag> element. This element has a <tag
            class="attribute">queryBinding</tag> attribute with an identifier for the language of
          assertion and context selector expressions.</para>

        <para>Originally Schematron was designed as a schema language solely on top of XSLT. The use
          of XPath and XSLT match expressions was generalized into the concept of a query language
          in the course of the ISO standardization process. <citation>JELLIFFE2002</citation>
          <citation>JELLIFFE2003</citation> A query language is defined by a <glossterm>query
            language binding</glossterm> that specifies the query language for rule context
          expressions and for assertion tests. The initial 2006 specification defined the query
          language binding for XSLT 1.0 <citation>XSLT1</citation> as the default query language.
          The later editions added normative query language bindings for XPath 2.0
            <citation>XPATH2</citation>, XSLT 2.0 <citation>XSLT2</citation>, XPath 3.0
            <citation>XPATH3</citation>, and XSLT 3.0 <citation>XSLT3</citation>. </para>
        <para>Assertion tests and context expressions are evaluated during validation. They depend
          on a properly initialized <glossterm>evaluation environment</glossterm>. Schematron
          provides two native elements to set up the environment for query language expressions. </para>
        <para>The repeatable <tag class="element">sch:ns</tag> element is a top-level element that
          defines the available namespace bindings. Namespace bindings have global scope. The
          repeatable <tag class="element">sch:let</tag> element defines the available variables and
          their values. Variables are globally available or scoped to the containing pattern or
          rule. </para>
        <para>Variables and namespaces can be seen as a common denominator of query languages. The
          2016 and 2020 updates to the specification, on the other hand, forbid the use of <tag
            class="element">sch:let</tag> for XPath 2.0 and 3.0. <footnote>
            <para>It is unclear why the working group felt the need to forbid the use of <tag
                class="element">sch:let</tag>. All versions of XPath support variable references in
              XPath expressions.</para>
          </footnote></para>
        <para>Defining namespace bindings and variables is not sufficient to evaluate an XSLT
          expression. To set up an evaluation environment for XSLT, Schematron explicitly allows the
          two elements <tag class="element">xsl:key</tag> and <tag class="element"
            >xsl:function</tag> as top-level elements.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Shortcomings</title>
        <para>Setting up the query language environment became more elaborate with new functionality
          introduced with XSLT 2.0 and later 3.0. The 2016 specification addressed this new
          functionality by allowing the <tag class="element">xsl:function</tag> declaration as an
          additional top-level element and by restricting the use of the new
            <function>fn:error()</function> function. Following the elimination of the result tree
          fragment data-type in favor of temporary trees it also made the <tag class="attribute"
            >value</tag> attribute of the <tag class="element">sch:let</tag> expression optional,
          allowing temporary trees as value. </para>
        <para>The 2020 specification did not add anything in support of XSLT 3.0. </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Corrections</title>
        <para>With regard to XSLT as query language three pieces are missing.</para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Support for data types</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>XSLT 2.0 introduced the capability to declare the required types of, among other
                things, variables. The type can be a built-in or a user-defined type imported from
                an XML schema. Schematron is currently missing both: The possibility to declare the
                required type of a variable and to import user-defined data types.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Setting up accumulators</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>XSLT 3.0 added accumulators as a new mechanism to capture and process data. An
                accumulator associates a series of values with nodes of the document tree. The value
                of an accumulator is obtained by calling the respective accumulator functions
                  <function>fn:accumulator-before()</function> and
                  <function>fn:accumulator-after()</function>. Although accumulators are designed
                for streaming transformations they can also be used with non-streaming
                transformations.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Loading user-defined libraries</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The addition of user-defined functions in XSLT 2.0 opened up the possibility of
                reusable, user-defined function libraries. XSLT 3.0 made the notion of user-defined
                libraries explicit by adding <glossterm>packages</glossterm>, collections of
                stylesheet modules with a controlled interface.</para>
              <para>Schematron lacks a way of including user-defined function libraries other than
                using schema composition instructions. But neither <tag class="element"
                  >sch:include</tag> nor <tag class="element">sch:extends</tag> is a good fit. The
                former inserts the content of an XML document in place of the element, the latter is
                only allowed to extend a rule. <footnote>
                  <para>See <xref linkend="composition"/></para>
                </footnote></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>To address these missing pieces the query language specification for XSLT should be
          expanded as follows:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>allow <tag class="element">xsl:include</tag> and <tag class="element"
                >xsl:import</tag> as top-level elements for the query languages XSLT 1.0, 2.0, and
              3.0</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>allow <tag class="element">xsl:schema-import</tag> as top-level elements for the
              query languages XSLT 2.0 and 3.0</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>allow an optional <tag class="attribute">as</tag> attribute on a sch:let
              instruction</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>allow <tag class="element">xsl:use-package</tag> and <tag class="element"
                >xsl:accumulator</tag> as top-level elements for the query language XSLT 3.0</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <table>
          <info>
            <title>Query language environment for XSLT (proposed additions marked with an
              asterisk)</title>
          </info>
          <tgroup cols="4">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry/>
                <entry>XSLT 1.0</entry>
                <entry>XSLT 2.0</entry>
                <entry>XSLT 3.0</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Indexes</entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">xsl:key</tag></entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">xsl:key</tag></entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">xsl:key</tag></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Functions</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">xsl:function</tag></entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">xsl:function</tag></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Namespaces</entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">sch:ns</tag></entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">sch:ns</tag></entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">sch:ns</tag></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Variables</entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">sch:let</tag></entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">sch:let</tag></entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">sch:let</tag></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>User-defined libraries*</entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">xsl:include</tag>, <tag class="element"
                  >xsl:import</tag></entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">xsl:include</tag>, <tag class="element"
                  >xsl:import</tag></entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">xsl:include</tag>, <tag class="element"
                  >xsl:import</tag>, <tag class="element">xsl:use-package</tag></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Typed variables*</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">sch:let</tag>/<tag class="attribute">as</tag></entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">sch:let</tag>/<tag class="attribute">as</tag></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>User-defined types*</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">sch:import-schema</tag></entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">sch:import-schema</tag></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Accumulators*</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry><tag class="element">xsl:accumulator</tag></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>

    </section>
    <section xml:id="composition">
      <title>Schema composition</title>
      <section>
        <title>Summary</title>
        <para>Schema composition is about arranging schemas, patterns, rules, and assertions to
          support different validation tasks and for the ease of maintenance by allowing reuse of
          assertions, rules, and patterns.</para>
        <para>Schematron provides four ways to compose a schema.</para>
        <para>An <glossterm>abstract rule</glossterm> is a named set of assertions and represented
          by a <tag class="element">sch:rule</tag> element without a context expression. It is
          scoped to the containing pattern. All rules of the same pattern can use a set of
          assertions by referencing the name of the abstract rule in the <tag class="attribute"
            >rule</tag> attribute of a <tag class="element">sch:extends</tag> element.</para>
        <para>A <glossterm>phase</glossterm> is a named set of patterns defined by a top-level <tag
            class="element">sch:phase</tag> element. Phases allow one schema document to cover
          multiple validation scenarios or needs.</para>
        <para>Schematron offers two mechanisms to use external definitions. The <tag class="element"
            >sch:include</tag> element can be used anywhere and has a <tag class="attribute"
            >href</tag> attribute that points to an external resource. The content of the resource
          is inserted in place of the <tag class="element">sch:include</tag> element.</para>
        <para>The second mechanism is build on top of the <tag class="element">sch:extends</tag>
          element. Instead of a <tag class="attribute">rule</tag> attribute naming an abstract rule,
          it may use a <tag class="attribute">href</tag> attribute pointing to an external resource.
          If the external resource is the same element as the <tag class="element"
          >sch:extends</tag> element’s parent, then the child nodes of the referenced element are
          inserted in place of the <tag class="element">sch:extends</tag> element. The use of <tag
            class="element">sch:extends</tag> however is still restricted to the <tag
            class="element">sch:rule</tag> element.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Shortcomings</title>
        <para>Consider the following case. A schema A, shown in <xref linkend="f.schema-a"/>,
          includes a pattern from a different schema B, shown in <xref linkend="f.schema-b"
          />.</para>
        <figure xml:id="f.schema-a">
          <title><filename>schema-a.sch</filename></title>
          <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="schema-a.sch" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="f.schema-b">
          <title><filename>schema-b.sch</filename></title>
          <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="schema-b.sch" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </figure>
        <para>Simply replacing the <tag class="element">sch:include</tag> element in A with the
          pattern from B does not produce a working schema.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para> The included pattern was written with the expectation that the prefix <tag
                class="prefix">ex</tag> is bound to <uri>http://example.com/ns1</uri>, but schema A
              uses the prefix <tag class="prefix">example</tag>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The rule context expression refers to a global variable
                <varname>allowedTypes</varname> which is not defined in A.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>In general, the interaction of schema composition with rule based validation is
          underspecified.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Corrections</title>
        <para>There is no simple correction. Schematron requires an inclusion mechanism that covers
          the interaction between variables and namespaces of combined schemas.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Reporting</title>

      <section>
        <title>Summary</title>
        <para>Schematron encourages the use of natural language descriptions targeted to human
          readers. This way validation can be more than just a binary distinction (document
          valid/invalid) but also support authors of in-progress documents with quick feedback on
          erroneous or unwanted document structure and content. </para>
        <para>To this effect an assertion test is associated with zero or more natural-language
          statements written in a lightweight templating language. The specification distinguishes
          between a primary statement given in the element content of an assertion element, and
          secondary statements or <glossterm>diagnostic</glossterm> given in the element content of
          a <tag class="element">sch:diagnostic</tag> element and referenced in a <tag
            class="attribute">diagnostics</tag> attribute of an assertion element.</para>

        <para>The 2016 revision added a mechanism for structured data targeted at machine rather
          than human consumption. Designed in the same fashion as diagnostics, an assertion may
          reference zero or more <tag class="element">sch:property</tag> elements in a <tag
            class="attribute">properties</tag> attribute. Each property element contains a template
          for structured data.</para>
        <para>The templates for natural-language statements and structured data are instantiated
          when the respective assertion fails. The templating language contains both, elements for
          text formatting (<tag class="element">sch:emph</tag>, <tag class="element">sch:span</tag>,
            <tag class="element">sch:dir</tag>) and elements that calculate values from the instance
          document (<tag>sch:value-of</tag>, <tag class="element">sch:name</tag>; <tag
            class="element">xsl:copy</tag>-of in <tag class="element">sch:property</tag> for the
          query languages XSLT 2.0 and 3.0).</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Shortcomings</title>
        <figure xml:id="multi-a">
          <title>Multi-lingual schema suggested by Annex G of ISO/IEC 19757-3:2020</title>
          <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="multilingual-1.sch" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </figure>
        <para>All three reporting elements are modelled as mixed-content elements. As a consequence,
          an assertion message or diagnostic can only specify one language with an <tag
            class="attribute">xml:lang</tag> attribute. The suggested mechanism for multi-lingual
          messages in Annex G of the specification, shown in <xref linkend="multi-a"/>, is
          cumbersome, at best. It suggests the schema author to define one diagnostic per localized
          message and reference them in the <tag class="attribute">diagnostics</tag> attribute of
          the respective assertion. Tobias Fischer <citation>FISCHER2017</citation> summarizes the
          biggest problem with this approach: Adding a localization requires adding the respective
          reference to every assertion.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Proposed corrections</title>
        <para>To address this shortcoming Schematron should make the abstraction of a specific
          message and its natural language content explicit. Rather than treating localized variants
          as different diagnostics, they should be treated as one diagnostic with different
          localized variants. A <tag class="element">sch:message</tag> element that wraps the
          mixed-content templates would do the trick.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Multi-lingual schema, improved</title>
          <programlisting language="xml"><xi:include href="multilingual-2.sch" parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>From ISO Schematron to Open Schematron?</title>
    <para>In the previous sections I discussed some shortcomings of the current ISO Schematron
      specification. Some could be fixed by simply amending the ISO specification, some like the
      lacking inclusion mechanism require more substantial work. Ideally, these issues would be
      addressed by a future 4th edition of the ISO Schematron specification. But alas, this seems
      unlikely.</para>
    <para>Maybe ISO Schematron becoming proprietary gives us the opportunity to start anew; or
      rather start with the core ideas of the Schematron assertion language and specify a rule based
      validation language that is not identical to, but intersects with ISO Schematron. This new
      Schematron language has the advantage of roughly 15 years of development in markup technology
      and roughly 15 years of ISO Schematron practice. </para>
    <para>It should be based on the XQuery and XPath Data Model 3.1 <citation>WALSH2017</citation>,
      a data model that includes maps, arrays, and support for strongly typed languages with a type
      system. It should also distinguish between a core specification and language extensions, and
      describe an extension mechanism that decouples the core from query language or use-case
      specific extensions such as streaming validation <citation>DZIURLAJ2021</citation> or
      interactive corrections <citation>KUTSCHERAUER2018</citation>. Given the rise of JSON
        <citation>JSON</citation> it should try to align with jsontron <citation>AMER2014</citation>
      and provide a query language binding for JSON-based path languages.</para>
    <para>Most importantly, it should again be an Open Standard.</para>
  </section>
  <bibliography>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>AMER2014</abbrev>Ali, Amer. 2014. <title>Schematron Based Semantic
        Constraints Specification Framework &amp; Validation Rules Engine for JSON</title>.
      https://raw.githubusercontent.com/amer-ali/jsontron/master/docs/Jsontron-presentation-v1.pdf. </bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>XPATH2</abbrev>Berglund, Anders, Scott Boag, Don Chamberlin, Mary F.
      Fernández, Michael Kay, Jonathan Robie, and Jérôme Siméon, eds. 2010. <title>XML Path Language
        (XPath) 2.0 (Second Edition)</title>. World Wide Web Consortium.
      http://www.w3.org/TR/2010/REC-xpath20-20101214/.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>XSLT1</abbrev>Clark, James, ed. 1999. <title>XSL Transformations (XSLT)
        Version 1.0</title>. World Wide Web Consortium.
      http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/REC-xslt-19991116.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>JSON</abbrev>Crockford, Douglas. 2017. <title>The JavaScript Object
        Notation (JSON) Data Interchange Format</title>. RFC 8259. Internet Engineering Task Force
      (IETF). https://tools.ietf.org/pdf/rfc8259.pdf.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>DZIURLAJ2021</abbrev>Dziurlaj, John. 2021. <title>Streaming Extensions for
        Schematron</title>. https://github.com/HiltonRoscoe/streamable-schematron.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>FISCHER2017</abbrev>Fischer, Tobias. 2017. <title>Localization Concept
        Needs Improvement</title>. https://github.com/Schematron/schematron/issues/40.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>JELLIFFE1999</abbrev>Jelliffe, Rick. 1999. <title>Schematron: An Interview
        with Rick Jelliffe</title> Interview by Simon St.Laurent.
      https://web.archive.org/web/20010619150155/http://www.xmlhack.com/read.php?item=121.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>JELLIFFE2002</abbrev>Jelliffe, Rick. 2002. <title>The Schematron Assertion
        Language 1.6</title>.
      https://web.archive.org/web/20061230150144/http://xml.ascc.net:80/resource/schematron/Schematron2000.html.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>JELLIFFE2003</abbrev>Jelliffe, Rick. 2003. <title>Schematron 1.5 to
        Schematron 1.6 to ISO Schematron</title>. June 21, 2003.
      http://www.topologi.com/resources/schematronUpgrades.html.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>KUTSCHERAUER2018</abbrev>Kutscherauer, Nico, and Octavian Nadolu, eds.
      2018. <title>Schematron Quick Fixes Specification</title>. Quick-fix support for XML Community
      Group. http://schematron-quickfix.github.io/sqf/spec/SQFSpec.html. </bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>XSLT3</abbrev>Kay, Michael, ed. 2017. <title>XSL Transformations (XSLT)
        Version 3.0</title>. World Wide Web Consortium.
      https://www.w3.org/TR/2017/REC-xslt-30-20170608/.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>XSLT2</abbrev>Kay, Michael, ed. 2021. <title>XSL Transformations (XSLT)
        Version 2.0 (Second Edition)</title>. World Wide Web Consortium.
      https://www.w3.org/TR/2021/REC-xslt20-20210330/.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>XPATH3</abbrev>Robie, Jonathan, Don Chamberlin, Micheal Dyck, and John
      Snelson, eds. 2014. <title>XML Path Language (XPath) 3.0</title>. World Wide Web Consortium.
      http://www.w3.org/TR/2014/REC-xpath-30-20140408/.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>SCHEMATRON2020</abbrev>
      <title>Information technology — Document Schema Definition Languages (DSDL) — Part 3:
        Rule-based validation, Schematron</title>, second edition, International Standard ISO/IEC
      19757-3:2020, Geneva, Switzerland : ISO</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed><abbrev>WALSH2017</abbrev>Walsh, Norman, John Snelson, and Andrew Coleman, eds.
      2017. <title>XQuery and XPath Data Model 3.1</title>. World Wide Web Consortium.
      https://www.w3.org/TR/2017/REC-xpath-datamodel-31-20170321/. </bibliomixed>
  </bibliography>
</article>
