<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
<info>
<title>The Cryptic Crossword Corpus Project:
first steps in establishing a markup vocabulary</title>
<titleabbrev>First steps</titleabbrev>
<author>
  <personname>Bethan S. T. Tovey</personname>
</author>
<abstract>
<para>In a quick crossword, the relationship between clue and answer
is usually simply definitional: the clue offers a definition or
description of, or a synonym for, the answer. In a cryptic crossword,
the relationship between clue and answer is significantly more
complex, and may be one of many types. Anagrams, puns, hidden words,
deletions, reversals, and other techniques are used, often in
combination. Every word in a clue does one of three jobs: a) defining
the answer (a synonym or definition of the answer word(s)); b)
producing part or all of the answer word; or c) indicating how the
words in b) are to be manipulated. It follows that each part of an
answer will relate back to one or more words in the clue from category
b), while the whole answer will relate to the word(s) in category a).
</para>
<para>This paper describes the early work of creating a markup scheme
which relates each part of a cryptic crossword clue to the relevant
part of its answer, as well as giving full linguistic detail for each
word. The aim of this project is to create a corpus of cryptic clues
and answers which can be explored to answer linguistic questions.</para>
</abstract>
</info>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>Cryptic crossword clues form a textual genre that remains surprisingly
under-theorized from almost any relevant linguistic standpoint
<phrase role="citations">(<link linkend="Pham2016" role="cite parencite">Pham, 2016</link>)</phrase>.
Two papers by semioticians stand out
as contributions to the understanding of the genre <phrase role="citations">(<link linkend="Greimas1967" role="cite parencite">Greimas, 1967</link>;
<link linkend="Vantu1991" role="cite parencite">Vântu, 1991</link>)</phrase>, as does a
recent corpus-linguistic analysis of crossword puzzles as a distinct
register <phrase role="citations">(<link linkend="Pham2016" role="cite parencite">Pham, 2016</link>)</phrase>. Articles examining the linguistic
playfulness and ambiguity of cryptic clues may be added to these as
examples of introductory explorations <phrase role="citations">(<link linkend="Cleary1996" role="cite parencite">Cleary, 1996</link>; <link linkend="Coffey1998" role="cite parencite">Coffey, 1998</link>; <link linkend="Rambousek2004" role="cite parencite">Rambousek, 2004</link>)</phrase>. Beyond this, many papers
published about crosswords (whether quick or cryptic) tend to be
psychological investigations of crossword solvers' intelligence or
other cognitive abilities, or the role of crosswords (and other
puzzles) in cognitive development and in preventing cognitive decline
<phrase role="citations">(e.g. <link linkend="Underwood1994" role="cite parencite">Underwood, 1994</link>; <link linkend="Lewis2006" role="cite parencite">Lewis, 2006</link>; <link linkend="Friedlander2009" role="cite parencite">Friedlander, 2009</link>; <link linkend="Nickerson2011" role="cite parencite">Nickerson, 2011</link>; <link linkend="Moxley2015" role="cite parencite">Moxley, 2015</link>; <link linkend="Friedlander2016" role="cite parencite">Friedlander, 2016</link>)</phrase>. The other common type of paper
is the description of computational approaches to writing or solving
crossword clues <phrase role="citations">(e.g. <link linkend="Williams1979" role="cite parencite">Williams, 1979</link>; <link linkend="Smith1986" role="cite parencite">Smith, 1986</link>; <link linkend="Littman2000" role="cite parencite">Littman, 2000</link>;
<link linkend="Hardcastle2007" role="cite parencite">Hardcastle, 2007</link>)</phrase>.</para>

<para>Could it be that the paucity of linguistic analyses of the
cryptic crossword can be attributed to a lack of interesting
linguistic features? After all, an entire puzzle's worth of crossword
clues contains relatively few words in total, and there is little
discursive linkage between individual clues. In the terms defined by
the foundational text-linguistic work by <phrase role="citations"><link linkend="HallidayHasan1976" role="cite textcite">Halliday (1976)</link></phrase>, a set of cryptic crossword
clues lacks <emphasis>texture</emphasis>: the network of linguistic
relationships between sentences that makes a coherent
<emphasis>text</emphasis>. A set of clues is a set of fragments, but
not a text.</para>

<para>Nevertheless, a number of authors have argued for the merit of
the cryptic crossword as an object of linguistic study. From the
perspective of semiotics, <phrase role="citations"><link linkend="Greimas1967" role="cite textcite">Greimas (1967)</link></phrase> suggests that the
crossword should be analysed on the same terms as other types of
aesthetic "communication différée" (p. 799) (<emphasis>delayed
communication</emphasis>). By this, he means uses of language (like
poetry) which are non-direct, and which necessitate a process of
decoding in order to achieve communication between the creator (known
as the "setter" of a cryptic crossword) and the audience. He notes
that the absence of grammatical predicates in French crossword clues
is the type of feature upon which a typology of the genre might be
built. Since the predicate carries many of the temporal specifics of a
sentence, as well as indicating the role of elements such as subject
and object, it is no surprise to find that the lack of a predicate is
also a feature of the English cryptic clue. <phrase role="citations"><link linkend="Stratmann1978" role="cite textcite">Stratmann (1978)</link></phrase> calls attention to the
relationship between the cryptic clue's encoding of meaning and the
literary tradition of Lewis Carroll and James Joyce. He links the
success and complexity of the cryptic crossword clue to specific
linguistic features of English, calling attention to the abundance of
short words and the lack of mandatory inflectional endings, aspects of
the language that make flexible clue-writing much easier. Indeed,
<phrase role="citations"><link linkend="Connor2013" role="cite textcite">Connor (2013b)</link></phrase> argues that English is "the best
crosswording language" (p.114) as a result of its large vocabulary and
rich range of synonyms (the result of large-scale borrowing from other
languages over more than a millennium). The cryptic crossword clue
benefits from the range of potential ambiguity residing in English
syonyms, as well as in the comparative lack of grammatical specificity
that <phrase role="citations"><link linkend="Stratmann1978" role="cite textcite">Stratmann (1978)</link></phrase> identifies. In an uninflected
language like English, it is no doubt easier to have a word that looks
like (say) a noun, but is intended by the setter as a verb; there are
few required word-endings that would give the game away. </para>

<para>Genre-theoretical approaches to the crossword have also been
successfully attempted. <phrase role="citations"><link linkend="Vantu1991" role="cite textcite">Vântu (1991)</link></phrase>, in an exploration of
Romanian crossword clues, argues that they may best be analyzed as
wordplay or as jokes. <phrase role="citations"><link linkend="Cleary1996" role="cite textcite">Cleary (1996)</link></phrase> calls English cryptic crosswords
"exercises in constructed ambiguity" (p.15). Like Vantu, he sees in
them a source for study of wordplay and linguistic humour, as well as
of the construction and comprehension of meaning. Finally,
<phrase role="citations"><link linkend="Pham2016" role="cite parencite">Pham’s, (2016)</link></phrase>
work on register and intertextuality is perhaps
the fullest exploration of the crossword in terms of linguistic
theory. Using a corpus of clues and answers, she argues that the use
of intertextual reference is a distinctive feature of the crossword as
a genre. She also establishes the distinctiveness of cryptic and
non-cryptic crosswords as sub-genres.</para>

<para>Evidently, there are sufficient grounds for considering the
cryptic crossword as an interesting linguistic object. The Cryptic
Crossword Corpus Project (CCCP) aims to provide a corpus-linguistic
basis for further work on this genre. The project will gather clues
from a range of different publications and crossword compilers,
including the big names such as <emphasis>The Times</emphasis> and
<emphasis>The Guardian</emphasis>, but also smaller and (perhaps) more
esoteric publications such as the satirical current-affairs magazine
<emphasis>Private Eye</emphasis> and the socialist newspaper
<emphasis>Morning Star</emphasis>. It may also prove possible to
include clues from cryptic crosswords outside Britain; for example,
<emphasis>The Sydney Morning Herald</emphasis> and <emphasis>The
Hindu</emphasis> both set a cryptic crossword, as (occasionally) does
<emphasis>The New York Times</emphasis>. For the moment, however, the
CCCP will focus on British crosswords.</para>

</section>
<section><title>A brief explanation of cryptic crosswords</title>

<para>Although crosswords are now to be found in many of the world's
languages, for the most part these are "quick" crosswords, whose clues
generally consist of a simple synonym of the target answer <phrase role="citations">(<link linkend="Connor2013" role="cite parencite">Connor, 2013b</link>)</phrase>. The first quick crossword is
generally agreed to have been published in New York in 1913; the
British cryptic was an offshoot, first found in the 1930s <phrase role="citations">(<link linkend="Arnot1981" role="cite parencite">Arnot, 1981</link>)</phrase>. The cryptic is largely a British
phenomenon; <phrase role="citations"><link linkend="Connor2013web" role="cite textcite">Connor (2013a)</link></phrase> suggests that this is partly
attributable to a British taste for "imagery of the nudge-and-wink
variety", toilet humour, and mild profanity, but also to a lack of
other solvers from whom to learn the conventions of the cryptic clue.
Learning how to solve cryptic crossword clues is a matter of practice,
and of learning the rules by which words are encoded into clues
<phrase role="citations">(<link linkend="Stratmann1978" role="cite parencite">Stratmann, 1978</link>)</phrase>. In order to understand the
specific markup needs of the CCCP, it will therefore be necessary to
take a brief tour of how target answers may be encoded by cryptic
crossword setters.</para>

<para>A quick clue for the location of this conference might simply
read "Capital city (6)' (the number in parentheses indicates how many
letters are in the target answer). There are, of course, a number of
capital cities with six letters; the quick-crossword solver relies on
the intersecting words to provide some of the letters needed to narrow
down the possibilities until the correct target is found. The
cryptic-crossword solver, in contrast, should be left in no doubt of
the correct answer, even if there are no intersecting letters
available to confirm it. This is achieved by careful writing of clues
that encode each target answer in two ways.</para>

<para>The commonest structure for a cryptic clue consists of the
<emphasis>definition</emphasis> and the <emphasis>subsidiary
indication</emphasis>. The definition provides some kind of synonym or
narrative definition of the target; the subsidiary indication encodes
the target in some other way. A frequent type of subsidiary indication
is the <emphasis>charade</emphasis>, in which letters or groups of
letters from the target are clued in sequence in the subsidiary
indication. If we take our "capital city" example, a charade clue
might read as follows: "Left Ontario with DeLillo for UK city" (6).
The clue breaks down as follows: <emphasis>L</emphasis>, a common
abbreviation for "left"; <emphasis>ON</emphasis>, the postal
abbreviation for "Ontario"; <emphasis>DON</emphasis>, the first name
of the American novelist DeLillo. Put together, these fragments
provide the target <emphasis>LONDON</emphasis>. "UK city", of course,
is the definition. Notice the words "with" and "for". These are not
mere filler. Each one has meaning in constructing the clue: "with"
indicates that the fragments can be placed together, and "for" is a
common indicator that what follows is the definition of the target. I
will call these types of words "metalanguage".</para>

<para>The function of the metalanguage is more prominent in this clue:
"City bird around nine doves, initially (6)". Here, the clue's first
word is the definition, and all that follows is the subsidiary
indication. We are looking for a word meaning "bird" which can be
placed around the initial letters of "nine doves". The bird is
<emphasis>LOON</emphasis>, and if we place <emphasis>ND</emphasis>
between its letters we again arrive at the target
<emphasis>LONDON</emphasis>. Again, every single word in the clue
serves a purpose. Finally, let us consider the following clue: "Melon
donut in possession of Julie (6)". Here we need to know that Julie
London was a famous singer, in order to understand that "Julie"
provides the definition component of the clue. The subsidiary
definition is what is known as a "container" type: the letters of the
target are inside ("in possession of") the words <emphasis>meLON
DONut</emphasis>.</para>

<para>These latter two clues show the ambiguity inherent in most
cryptic clues, and how linguistic features are exploited to create
that ambiguity. The apparent noun phrase "city bird" leads the reader
away from the necessary understanding that the split between
definition and subsidiary indication happens between the two words. We
can see, also, that the cryptic crossword setter is permitted to play
fast and loose with punctuation: a more honest punctuation of the clue
as "City: bird around nine doves initially" would make the roles of
the various words clearer. Similarly, the metalanguage in the final
clue is most easily read as suggesting that the donut is in Julie's
possession, whereas the solution requires understanding that "in
possession of" works in reverse here. Either reading is perfectly
syntactically allowable in English, but the more obvious reading is
the wrong one for finding the target answer.</para>

<para>These examples, I hope, portray a distinctive characteristic of
a well-written cryptic clue: the solver should be left in no doubt
that her answer is correct <phrase role="citations">(<link linkend="Pham2016" role="cite parencite">Pham, 2016</link>)</phrase>. The subsidiary
indication makes it clear that no other answer is possible, by
providing specific (albeit heavily encoded) instructions about the
physical makeup of the target answer <phrase role="citations">(<link linkend="Coffey1998" role="cite parencite">Coffey, 1998</link>)</phrase>. Not all clues
consist of a definition and subsidiary indication, however. So-called
"double-definition" clues are also popular. These offer two
definitions, incorporated into an apparently single syntactic unit,
which approach the target answer from two different directions. An
example from <emphasis>The Times</emphasis> will exemplify this type
of clue: "Alert goalkeeper may dive thus (2, 3, 4)". The answer is "ON
THE BALL", for which "alert" is a synonym, and "goalkeeper may dive
thus" is a descriptive definition. Once the solver has hit upon this
answer, it is quite clear that nothing else will fit the bill; there
is no other phrase that is defined by both of the definitions. Another
example, this time from the <emphasis>Daily Mail</emphasis>, shows the
dangers of attempting this type of clue: "Guess there's no proof for
it (10)". The answer, "CONJECTURE", is not particularly obvious. The
two definitions, the synonym "Guess" and the descriptive "there's no
proof for it" could apply to many similar words. It will be
interesting to see whether intuitions about what makes for a good and
a bad clue can be supported by linguistic evidence. For example, it
seems possible that a good double-definition clue needs to have a
certain amount of semantic distance between the two definitions. If
these are too close, there's a risk (as in the Daily Mail example)
that the clue ends up being too broad. It is the intersection of
apparently quite different synonyms or definitions which both apply to
a single target that makes for a good clue.</para>

</section>
<section><title>Developing the markup vocabulary for CCCP</title>

<para>The previous section of this paper has given an outline of a
sample of the elements that are used to construct a cryptic crossword
clue. In developing a markup vocabulary for CCCP, it has been
necessary to consider how these elements (as well as others not
discussed above for reasons of space) relate to each other, and which
of them are required in order to give a comprehensive account of the
structure of a clue. There are, of course, elements above the level of
the clue that could also be captured, such as the source of the
crossword, the name of the setter, the date on which the crossword
appeared, and so on. </para>
 
<para>Making decisions about how much detail to include required some
predictions about the questions that might be asked of the corpus data
at a later stage of the project. <phrase role="citations"><link linkend="Cleary1996" role="cite textcite">Cleary (1996)</link></phrase> suggested some
possible avenues for research, including examining differences between
setters, and the use of polysemous words both in clues and as targets.
To this might be added comparison of the "house styles" of various
newspapers, comparison of the language of clues at different points in
time, and the use of words with ambiguous part of speech. Evidently,
these questions require marking up not only the structural features of
the clue itself, but also of the name of the publication, the setter,
the date, and the parts of speech of individual word. Since I am also
interested in how various fragments of the target answers are commonly
(or, indeed, uncommonly) represented in the subsidiary indications,
there also needs to be a way to link each part of the clue to the
corresponding part of the answer.</para>

<para>The following example shows a single clue and answer pair within
the root <literal>&lt;corpus&gt;</literal> element:</para>

<programlisting>&lt;corpus&gt;
    &lt;publication pub="independent" type="anthology" ISBN="0550101756" pubdate="2005"&gt;
        &lt;puzzle id="1" setter="Aelred"&gt;
            &lt;item id="4"&gt;
                &lt;clue&gt;
                    &lt;subsidiary&gt;
                        &lt;source class="definition" id="1"&gt;
                            &lt;word pos="JJ"&gt;Feeble&lt;/word&gt;
                            &lt;word pos="NN"&gt;type&lt;/word&gt;
                        &lt;/source&gt;
                        &lt;meta class="locator" type="concatenation"&gt;
                            &lt;word pos="VVZ"&gt;adopts&lt;/word&gt;
                        &lt;/meta&gt;
                        &lt;source class="translation" id="2"&gt;
                            &lt;word pos="DT"&gt;the&lt;/word&gt;
                        &lt;/source&gt;
                        &lt;meta class="operator" type="translation"&gt;
                            &lt;word pos="JJ"&gt;French&lt;/word&gt;
                        &lt;/meta&gt;
                    &lt;/subsidiary&gt;
                    &lt;def type="hypernym"&gt;
                        &lt;word pos="NN"&gt;headdress&lt;/word&gt;
                    &lt;/def&gt;
                &lt;/clue&gt;
                &lt;solution words="1" letters="6" text="wimple" pos="NN"&gt;
                    &lt;unit id="1"&gt;WIMP&lt;/unit&gt;
                    &lt;unit id="2"&gt;LE&lt;/unit&gt;
                &lt;/solution&gt;
            &lt;/item&gt;
        &lt;/puzzle&gt;
    &lt;/publication&gt;
&lt;/corpus&gt;</programlisting>

<para>(N.B. for ease of reading, part-of-speech tagging is omitted
from all examples below).</para>

<para>The first element within the root,
<literal>&lt;publication&gt;</literal>, captures the published source
for the crosswords. In this case, the source is an anthology, so the
ISBN and the publication date are also captured, as is the publication
- in this case, <emphasis>The Independent</emphasis>. Within this
element, the first <literal>&lt;puzzle&gt;</literal> element has an
<emphasis role="bold">id</emphasis> attribute (to indicate its place
within the anthology) and a <emphasis role="bold">setter</emphasis>
attribute. This attribute must often have the value "anon", because
many anthologies fail to identify the specific setter of each puzzle.
Each <literal>&lt;puzzle&gt;</literal> element contains a number of
<literal>&lt;item&gt;</literal> elements; these contain the clue and
answer pairs.</para>

<para>The clue in the above example has the structure defined in
section 2 above: a subsidiary indication and a definition. These are
captured inside the <literal>&lt;clue&gt;</literal> element, as
<literal>&lt;subsidiary&gt;</literal> and
<literal>&lt;def&gt;</literal>. The attribute <emphasis role="bold">type</emphasis> on <literal>&lt;def&gt;</literal>
indicates whether the definition element is a straight synonym, a
phrase, a narrative definition, or some other kind of semantic
relative of the target answer; in this case, the definition is a
hypernym (a term that is more general than the target answer). This
information will be useful for exploring questions of how different
kinds of definition might affect clue difficulty.</para>

<para>The child elements of <literal>&lt;subsidiary&gt;</literal> are
<literal>&lt;source&gt;</literal> (for the words that are manipulated
to restructure the target answer) and <literal>&lt;meta&gt;</literal>
(for metalanguage). The <literal>source</literal> attribute <emphasis role="bold">class</emphasis> indicates how the word must be
manipulated in order to produce an answer (or answer fragment). In
this example, the first <literal>&lt;source&gt;</literal> is a
definition of its corresponding fragment, and the second must be
translated. The attribute <emphasis role="bold">class</emphasis> on
<literal>&lt;meta&gt;</literal> indicates the function performed by
the metalanguage. In this case, the first example is of the "locator"
class, and the "concatenation" subtype, which indicates that the
result of the second <literal>&lt;source&gt;</literal> is placed after
the first. The second example is an operator, and an additional
<emphasis role="bold">type</emphasis> attribute tells us that the
operation required is translation. Finally, each individual word in
the clue is enclosed in a <literal>&lt;word&gt;</literal> element,
with an attribute indicating part of speech. The part-of-speech tagset
used is the Penn Treebank tagset as modified for use in the Sketch
Engine corpus software <phrase role="citations">(<link linkend="SketchEngine" role="cite parencite">, </link>)</phrase>. The
<literal>&lt;solution&gt;</literal> element contains basic information
such as number of words, number of letters, and the plain text of the
target answer, as well as its part of speech (if that can be
determined). The target itself is then broken down into
<literal>&lt;unit&gt;</literal> elements, each of which has an
<emphasis role="bold">id</emphasis> attribute whose value corresponds
to the <emphasis role="bold">id</emphasis> of the
<literal>&lt;source&gt;</literal> element from which it was produced.
For a double-definition clue, the markup looks a little
different:</para>

<programlisting>&lt;item id="13"&gt;
    &lt;clue&gt;
        &lt;def type="synonym"&gt;Alert&lt;/def&gt;
        &lt;def type="descriptive"&gt;goalkeeper may dive thus&lt;/def&gt;
    &lt;/clue&gt;
    &lt;solution words="3" letters="9" text="on the ball" pos="PHRASE"&gt;
        &lt;unit&gt;ON THE BALL&lt;/unit&gt;
    &lt;/solution&gt;
&lt;/item&gt;</programlisting>

<para>Here there are two <literal>&lt;def&gt;</literal> elements, and
the single <literal>&lt;unit&gt;</literal> element is not given an
<emphasis role="bold">id</emphasis> attribute, as it is assumed that
definitions always point towards the answer.</para>

<para>Clues with "container" type <emphasis role="bold">locator</emphasis> class metalanguage generally require
embedding one <literal>&lt;unit&gt;</literal> within another in the
answer. This is easily achieved by making it legal for one
<literal>&lt;unit&gt;</literal> to have another as a child
element:</para>

<programlisting>&lt;item id="6"&gt;
    &lt;clue&gt;
        &lt;def type="descriptive"&gt;Irish leader&lt;/def&gt;
        &lt;subsidiary&gt;
            &lt;source class="anagram" id="1"&gt;is a cheat&lt;/source&gt;
            &lt;punct&gt;,&lt;/punct&gt;
            &lt;meta class="operator" type="anagram"&gt;worried&lt;/meta&gt;
            &lt;meta class="locator" type="container"&gt;about&lt;/meta&gt;
            &lt;source class="abbreviation" id="2"&gt;nothing&lt;/source&gt;
        &lt;/subsidiary&gt;
    &lt;/clue&gt;
    &lt;solution words="1" letters="9" text="Taoiseach" pos="NP"&gt;
        &lt;unit id="1"&gt;TA&lt;unit id="2"&gt;O&lt;/unit&gt;ISEACH&lt;/unit&gt;
    &lt;/solution&gt;
&lt;/item&gt;</programlisting>

<para>Another distinctive markup requirement is found in <emphasis>The
Sun</emphasis>, which publishes "Two-Speed Crosswords". The same grid
of target answers is offered with two sets of clues: one quick, and
one cryptic. On the principle that it is always better to capture too
much information than too little, I decided to add the quick clues in
an initial <literal>&lt;quick&gt;</literal> element for these
crosswords:</para>

<programlisting>&lt;item id="2"&gt;
    &lt;clue&gt;
        &lt;quick&gt;On fire&lt;/quick&gt;
        &lt;subsidiary&gt;
            &lt;source class="literal" id="1"&gt;A&lt;/source&gt;
            &lt;source class="synonym" id="2"&gt;fair&lt;/source&gt;
        &lt;/subsidiary&gt;
        &lt;def type="synonym"&gt;land&lt;/def&gt;
    &lt;/clue&gt;
    &lt;solution words="1" letters="6" text="alight" pos="VV"&gt;
        &lt;unit id="1"&gt;A&lt;/unit&gt;
        &lt;unit id="2"&gt;LIGHT&lt;/unit&gt;
    &lt;/solution&gt;
&lt;/item&gt;</programlisting>

</section>
<section><title>Conclusion</title>

<para>The markup vocabulary I have sketched out above is by no means
fixed at this stage. As more clues from more sources are added to the
corpus, it may be that changes are needed in order to accommodate the
quirks of a particular author. There are also some issues for which I
am not sure that satisfactory solutions have yet been found. Perhaps
the largest of these issues is that of reference. Some clues may refer
to other clues within the same puzzle, using the answer to another
clue to construct their own definitions or subsidiary indications. It
is clear that there needs to be a way to indicate such cross-reference
within a puzzle. But what about exophoric reference (reference to
things outside the text)? If we want to understand how linguistic
differences affect the difficulty level of various puzzles, for
example, we might take a discourse-analytic perspective and consider
how the clues reference culture outside the bounds of the puzzle
itself. For example, the "LONDON" clues discussed above refer to two
cultural figures: Don DeLillo and Julie London. These are evidently
figures from different domains - literature and popular music,
respectively. Is this information useful? If so, how can it be
captured? Depth of information is also a question: is it enough to
specify the domain from which these figures come, or would it also be
useful to know the period in which they were active? Should their
status as real-life figures (as opposed to fictional characters) also
be captured?</para>

<para>The answer to these questions, and to others that will
undoubtedly arise, will need a certain amount of trial and error, and
answers will emerge during the process of marking up more and more
clues. Evidently, the initial stages outlined here are just the
beginning of what promises to be a complex but rewarding
project.</para>

</section>

<bibliography>
<bibliomixed xml:id="Arnot1981" xreflabel="Arnot 1981">Arnot, M. (<date>1981</date>). <citetitle>A history of the crossword
puzzle.</citetitle> London: Macmillan.
</bibliomixed>
<bibliomixed xml:id="Cleary1996" xreflabel="Cleary 1996">Cleary, J. (<date>1996</date>). Misleading contexts: the construction
of ambiguity in the cryptic crossword clue. <citetitle>Edinburgh Working Papers
in Applied Linguistics</citetitle>, <volumenum>7</volumenum>, 14–29.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Coffey1998" xreflabel="Coffey 1998">Coffey, S. (<date>1998</date>). Linguistic aspects of the cryptic
crossword. <citetitle>English Today</citetitle>, <volumenum>14</volumenum>(1), 14–18.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Connor2013web" xreflabel="Connor 2013a">Connor, A. (<date>2013a</date>, December). <citetitle>Are cryptic crosswords too
rude for americans?</citetitle> Retrieved June 4, 2018, from
https://www.theguardian.com/crosswords/crossword-blog/2013/
dec/18/cryptic-crosswords-too-rude-for-americans-puzzle
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Connor2013" xreflabel="Connor 2013b">Connor, A. (<date>2013b</date>). <citetitle>Two girls, one on each knee</citetitle>. London: Penguin.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Friedlander2009" xreflabel="Friedlander 2009">Friedlander, K. J. &amp; Fine, P. (<date>2009</date>). Expertise in
cryptic crossword performance: an exploratory survey. In A.
Williamon, S. Pretty, &amp; R. Buck (Eds.), <citetitle>Proceedings of the
international symposium on performance science, Auckland</citetitle> (pp.
279–284). European Association of Conservatoires (AEC). Utrecht.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Friedlander2016" xreflabel="Friedlander 2016">Friedlander, K. J. &amp; Fine, P. A. (<date>2016</date>). The grounded
expertise components approach in the novel area of cryptic crossword
solving. <citetitle>Frontiers in psychology</citetitle>, <volumenum>7</volumenum>, 1–21.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Greimas1967" xreflabel="Greimas 1967">Greimas, A. J. (<date>1967</date>). L’écriture cruciverbiste. In <citetitle>To
honor roman jakobson: essays on the occasion of his seventieth
birthday</citetitle> (Vol. 1, pp. 799–815). La Haye: Mouton.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="HallidayHasan1976"  xreflabel="Halliday &amp; Hasan 1976">Halliday, M. A. K. &amp; Hasan, R. (<date>1976</date>). <citetitle>Cohesion in
English</citetitle>. London: Longman.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Hardcastle2007" xreflabel="Hardcastle 2007">Hardcastle, D. (<date>2007</date>). Cryptic crossword
clues: generating text with a hidden meaning. In <citetitle>Proceedings of the
eleventh european workshop on natural language generation</citetitle> (pp.
147–150). Association for Computational Linguistics.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Kilgarriff2004" xreflabel="Kilgarriff 2004">Kilgarriff, A., Rychlý, P., Smr, P., &amp; Tugwell, D.
(<date>2004</date>). Itri-04-08 the sketch engine. <citetitle>Information Technology</citetitle>.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Lewis2006" xreflabel="Lewis 2006">Lewis, M. B. (<date>2006</date>). Eye-witnesses should not do cryptic
crosswords prior to identity parades. <citetitle>Perception</citetitle>,
<volumenum>35</volumenum>(10), 1433–1436.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Littman2000" xreflabel="Littman 2000">Littman, M. L. (<date>2000</date>). Computer language games. In T.
Marsland &amp; I. Frank (Eds.), <citetitle>International conference on computers
and games</citetitle> (pp. 396–404). Lecture notes in computer science. Berlin:
Springer.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Moxley2015" xreflabel="Moxley 2015">Moxley, J. H., Ericsson, K. A., Scheiner, A., &amp;
Tuffiash, M. (<date>2015</date>). The effects of experience and disuse on crossword
solving. <citetitle>Applied Cognitive Psychology</citetitle>, <volumenum>29</volumenum>,
73–80.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Nickerson2011" xreflabel="Nickerson 2011">Nickerson, R. S. (<date>2011</date>). Five down, absquatulated:
crossword puzzle clues to how the mind works. <citetitle>Psychonomic bulletin
&amp; review</citetitle>, <volumenum>18</volumenum>, 217–241.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="SketchEngine" xreflabel="Sketch Engine"><citetitle>English TreeTagger PoS tagset with Sketch Engine
modifications</citetitle>. (n.d.). Retrieved from
https://www.sketchengine.eu/english-treetagger-pipeline-2/
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Pham2016" xreflabel="Pham 2016">Pham, T. (<date>2016</date>). The register of English crossword
puzzles: studies in intertextuality. In C. Schubert &amp; C.
Sanchez-Stockhammer (Eds.), <citetitle>Variational text linguistics: revisiting
register in English</citetitle> (pp. 111–136). Berlin: De Gruyter Mouton.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Rambousek2004" xreflabel="Rambousek 2004">Rambousek, J. (<date>2004</date>). Between language play and language
game. <citetitle>Theory and Practice in English Studies</citetitle>,
<volumenum>2</volumenum>, 165–171.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Smith1986" xreflabel="Smith 1986">Smith, G. &amp; Du Boulay, J. (<date>1986</date>). The generational of
cryptic crossword clues. <citetitle>The Computer Journal</citetitle>,
<volumenum>29</volumenum>(3), 282–284.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Stratmann1978" xreflabel="Stratmann 1978">Stratmann, G. (<date>1978</date>). Versuch uber die Kunst des
britischen Crossword und Appell, dieselbe zu importieren (nebst einem
eingedeutschten Exempel). <citetitle>anglistik und englischunterricht</citetitle>,
<volumenum>4</volumenum>,
125–136.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Underwood1994" xreflabel="Underwood 1994">Underwood, G., Deihim, C., &amp; Batt, V. (<date>1994</date>). Expert
performance in solving word puzzles: from retrieval cues to crossword
clues. <citetitle>Applied Cognitive Psychology</citetitle>,
<volumenum>8</volumenum>(6), 531–548.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Vantu1991" xreflabel="Vântu 1991">Vântu, I. (<date>1991</date>). La sémiotique des mots croisés. Revue
roumaine de linguistique, 23–29.
</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="Williams1979" xreflabel="Williams 1979">Williams, P. W. &amp; Woodhead, D.
(<date>1979</date>). Computer assisted analysis of cryptic crosswords. <citetitle>The Computer
Journal</citetitle>, <volumenum>22</volumenum>(1), 67–70.
</bibliomixed>
</bibliography>

</article>
