<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <title>An improved diff3 format using XML: diff3x</title>
    <info>
        <abstract>
            <para>There is no doubt that the diff and diff3 format has established itself as a
                well-used de-facto standard. It might seem presumptuous to suggest that it could be
                improved, or indeed that it needs to be improved. However, the original premise of
                line-based text files as the subject matter is now out of date with more structured
                information being the norm. Often this is in the form of programming source code
                where the layout tends to remain fairly consistent through edit cycles, but
                increasing use of JSON and XML pose particular difficulties for the simple
                line-based structure of diff3.</para>
            <para>In our paper at MarkupUK in 2019, we discussed some of the issues and suggested
                some minor improvements to diff3. These changes suffered from the common complaints
                of a retro-fit in that they did not sit comfortably with the original and only did
                half a job. The prevalence of GUIs also suggest that the actual syntax of a diff
                file is not as important as it was in that the emphasis has changed from human
                readability to interchange between two applications, for example between a git
                'merge driver' and a git 'mergetool'. For these reasons it seemed better to consider
                a different approach using the tools and formats that are now in common use, for
                example XML or JSON.</para>
            <para>What might diff3 look like as an XML format? Would the advantages of a new format
                make it worth swapping from the tried and tested diff3? Could existing GUI software
                easily adapt to a new format and, perhaps, even be simpler as a result?</para>
        </abstract>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Robin</firstname>
                <surname>La Fontaine</surname>
            </personname>
            <personblurb>
                <para>Robin is the founder and CEO of DeltaXML. Robin's original academic training
                    was in Engineering Science from Oxford University and an MSc in Computer
                    Science. His background includes computer aided design software in mechanical,
                    electrical and electronic applications, and solar energy system simulation.
                    Since founding DeltaXML, he has been addressing the challenges and exploring the
                    opportunities associated with information change in data and documents.</para>
            </personblurb>
            <affiliation><orgname>DeltaXML</orgname></affiliation>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Nigel</firstname>
                <surname>Whitaker</surname>
            </personname>
            <personblurb>
                <para>Nigel is the Chief Architect at DeltaXML and explores new product development
                    as well as the more mundane aspects of software development. He studied Physics
                    and Computer Science at Manchester University, where after his PhD, he worked on
                    computer aided design for electronics.</para>
            </personblurb>
            <address>
                <street>DeltaXML</street><street>Malvern Hills Science Park</street>
                <postcode>WR14 3SZ</postcode>
                <city>Malvern</city>
                <country>UK</country>
            </address>
            <affiliation><orgname>DeltaXML</orgname></affiliation>
        </author>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction and Background</title>
        <para>This paper is a sequel to "An Improved diff3 Format for Changes and Conflicts in Tree Structures"
            [<biblioref linkend="diff3format"/>] and again is focused on the diff3
            format rather than the diff3 executable application. In this paper we will develop an
            XML alternative to the diff3 format from GNU diffutils [<biblioref linkend="diffutils"/>].
            There are many possible outputs from diff3 but the one we are interested in is the one
            that provides a merged file result with conflicts marked up, i.e. the '-m' option on the
            command line. </para>
        <para>Many users do not view diff3 data directly or invoke diff3 itself, instead it is often
            invoked by a version control systems such as git or mercurial when the users merge a
            branch, graft or cherry-pick, rebase or change branches with working directory
            changes.</para>
        <para>A characteristic that we seek from the start is that as the number of changes tends to
      zero, so the diff file tends to resemble the original files. This is desirable in that minimal
      processing is needed for few changes and human understanding is improved simply because when
      the diff and the original files are very similar they will look very similar.</para>
        <para>We distinguish between the 'carrier' syntax which is the diff3 alternative, and the
            'payload' which is the content of the file(s) being compared or merged.</para>
        <para>In our previous paper, we considered both XML and JSON as a candidate for the carrier
            syntax and established that XML is a more natural fit, with the payload of the original
            files being, typically, not XML. However, of course this could be applied to XML itself
            and then there is likely to be at a human readability level a confusion between the
            payload and the carrier, and we will look at that in this paper. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Developing an XML syntax for diff3x</title>
        <para>First we look at the trivial but important example of a diff3 for three identical
            files, i.e. there are no changes. As we are using XML there is a minimum overhead of the
            start and end tags, so if the example files are all the same, as shown below:<table
                frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1">
                <title>Three identical files</title>
                <tgroup cols="3" align="left">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>A.txt</entry>
                            <entry>O.txt</entry>
                            <entry>B.txt</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <screen xml:space="preserve">1 
2
3
4
5
6</screen>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <screen xml:space="preserve">1
2
3
4
5
6</screen>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <screen xml:space="preserve">1
2
3
4
5
6</screen>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table></para>
        <para>The XML representation would be as shown below and note that white space needs to be
            preserved, or CDATA could be
            used.<programlisting language="xml">&lt;diff3x>1
2
3
4
5
6&lt;/diff3x></programlisting></para>
        <para>Now we can move on to represent actual changes.</para>
        <para>We need an example to show the syntax and we will use the same example as in the
      previous paper because it also allows us to illustrate how the XML syntax can potentially
      represent a richer view of the differences. For clarity we repeat the example here. The
      example is based on this paper, "A Formal Investigation of Diff3" [<biblioref linkend="FormalDiff3"
      />]. The example consists of three text files with numbers on each line, the files are denoted
      A.txt, B.txt and the 'old' file O.txt as shown below:<table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" xml:id="mismatched-sequences">
        <title>Mismatched sequences</title>
        <tgroup cols="3" align="left">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>A.txt</entry>
              <entry>O.txt</entry>
              <entry>B.txt</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <screen xml:space="preserve">1 
4
5
2
3
6</screen>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <screen xml:space="preserve">1
2
3
4
5
6</screen>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <screen xml:space="preserve">1
2
4
5
3
6</screen>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </para>
        <para>The way these are combined into the two diffs, A+O and O+B are shown in the table
            below. </para>
        <para>
            <inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="tables.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject></para>
        <para>The last three columns show how the two diffs are combined. Note that the yellow match
            shows where all three files align - and this is important because it is the data between
            these alignment points that are considered as units of change. Now we can look at the
            diff3 output using the -m
            option:<screen xml:space="preserve">1
4
5
2
&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; A.txt
3
||||||| O.txt
3
4
5
=======
4
5
3
>>>>>>> B.txt
6</screen></para>
        <para>How might this look as XML? Because we are only looking at a maximum of three files it
            seems reasonable to have a specific element to represent each one. However, we also need
            to record the original file names and these could be shown as attributes on the root
            element. So, the above might be represented in XML as
            follows.<programlisting language="xml">&lt;diff3x a="A.txt" b="B.txt" o="O.txt">1
4
5
2&lt;choice3>&lt;a>
3&lt;/a>&lt;o>
3
4
5&lt;/o>&lt;b>
4
5
3&lt;/b>&lt;/choice3>
6&lt;/diff3x></programlisting></para>
        <para>The element <code language="xml">&lt;choice3></code> introduces a three-way choice between the three original
            files.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Showing Non-conflicting Changes</title>
            <para>Now that we have moved into an XML syntax world, we have the opportunity for a
                richer representation to show non-conflicting changes. It is often useful to see
                these to understand how a merge has been handled and provides more context when
                resolving conflicts. In this example we could show the origin of the '4 5' data that
                was added by A.</para>
            <para>To show this we need to have elements defined for the limited combinations of the
                three input files. We can do this as <code language="xml">&lt;ao></code> for data in both O and A, and similarly
                <code language="xml">&lt;ab></code>, <code language="xml">&lt;ob></code>. We do not need <code language="xml">&lt;aob></code> because any lines matched across all three
                will be present as a child of the root element. Any non-conflicting change will have
                one of these dual origin elements as one of the two options. As these are
                non-conflicting changes, they are a resolved choice and we can indicate this with an
                attribute to show which option has been included. This attribute could also be used
                to indicate which option or options in a conflicting choice is to be included in the
                final result. A GUI might provide a user with the ability to undo this
                choice.</para>
            <para>
                <programlisting language="xml">&lt;diff3x a="A.txt" b="B.txt" o="O.txt">1&lt;choice2>&lt;a include="true">
4
5&lt;/a>&lt;ob/>&lt;/choice2>
2&lt;choice3>&lt;a>
3&lt;/a>&lt;o>
3
4
5&lt;/o>&lt;b>
4
5
3&lt;/b>&lt;/choice3>
6&lt;/diff3x></programlisting>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Showing linked changes to JSON Structure in diff3x</title>
            <para>For JSON, the issue of handling curly braces (for objects) and square brackets
                (for arrays) is similar to XML start and end tags. Again, some representation of
                connected change is needed to maintain syntactic correctness. </para>
            <para>Object members and array members are comma separated and this is tricky to get
                right in some situations. The syntax is shown below.</para>
            <para>
                <screen xml:space="preserve">object = begin-object [ member *( value-separator member ) ]
               end-object
array = begin-array [ value *( value-separator value ) ] end-array

These are the six structural characters:
  begin-array = ws %x5B ws ; [ left square bracket
  begin-object = ws %x7B ws ; { left curly bracket
  end-array = ws %x5D ws ; ] right square bracket
  end-object = ws %x7D ws ; } right curly bracket
  name-separator = ws %x3A ws ; : colon
  value-separator = ws %x2C ws ; , comma

Insignificant whitespace is allowed before or after any of the six
structural characters.
ws = *(
       %x20 / ; Space
       %x09 / ; Horizontal tab
       %x0A / ; Line feed or New line
       %x0D ) ; Carriage return</screen>
            </para>
            <para>Here is an example of a change to an array of strings.<table frame="all"
                    rowsep="1" colsep="1">
                    <title>JSON structural change</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3" align="left">
                        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.05*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.1*"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>A.txt</entry>
                                <entry>O.txt</entry>
                                <entry>B.txt</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <programlisting language="javascript">[[12,13,14],20,21,22]</programlisting>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <programlisting language="javascript">[12,13,14,20,21,22]</programlisting>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <programlisting language="javascript">[[12,13,14,20,21,22]]</programlisting>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>This could be represented in the diff3 format as shown below, but note that
                this is not how diff3 would process the above files which each have a single line.
                However the result below could be generated by careful use of line breaks in the
                input files.
                <screen xml:space="preserve">[
&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; A.txt
[
||||||| O.txt
 
=======

>>>>>>> B.txt
 
&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; A.txt

||||||| O.txt
 
=======
[
>>>>>>> B.txt
12,13,14
&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; A.txt
]
||||||| O.txt
 
=======

>>>>>>> B.txt
,20,21,22
&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; A.txt

||||||| O.txt
 
=======
]
>>>>>>> B.txt
]</screen></para>
            <para>The above will only produce syntactically correct results if the correct choices
                are made, which is not easy. It is also not easy to see what is going on in the
                diff3 file because of the extra whitespace lines that have to be inserted to make
                this work.</para>
            <para>We introduce here a way to connect the relevant consistent choices so that if the
                '[' is selected then the appropriate choice of the end ']' is also made
                automatically. </para>
            <para>A choice consists of one or more options. An option may have an id. An option may
                also have a select attribute which provides a boolean value made up of one or a
                combination of other ids and if these are 'true', i.e. have been chosen to be
                included, then this option is selected automatically. </para>
            <para>This could be represented in diff3x as shown below. We show here the id attribute
        on an option to identify it uniquely within the file. We then use that id to reference that
        option where another option needs to be linked to it. In this case, the '[' in the A.txt has
                <code>id="a42"</code> and this is then referenced in the select attribute of the corresponding ']' option
        later in the file. Similarly the pair of square brackets in B.txt are linked with the id
        "b44".<programlisting language="xml">&lt;diff3x a="A.txt" b="B.txt" o="O.txt">
[
&lt;choice2>
&lt;a id="a42">[&lt;/a>
&lt;ob/>&lt;/choice2>
&lt;choice2>
&lt;b id="b44">[&lt;/b>
&lt;ao/>&lt;/choice2>
12,13,14
&lt;choice2>
&lt;a select="a42">]&lt;/a>
&lt;ob/>&lt;/choice2>
,20,21,22
&lt;choice2>
&lt;b select="b44">]&lt;/b>
&lt;ao/>&lt;/choice2>
]&lt;/diff3x></programlisting></para>
            <para>Note that the '[' in A could be selected either instead of or as well as the '['
        in B even though they are at the same position in the array. Whichever choice is made, the
        other choices with a select attribute identifying the same id are chosen and the result is
        syntactically correct. This is a powerful way to represent connected choices.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Representing JSON Separator Change in diff3x</title>
            <para>The problem with separators is that they cannot consistently be associated with
                either the start or the end of each item (member for object and value for array)
                because if there is only one item then no separator is needed. Therefore maintaining
                correct syntax when items are added or deleted is not trivial. As mentioned above,
                the diff3 format does not allow consecutive choices without 'anchor' data between,
                so it is necessary to group consecutive items that may be added or deleted into one
                choice. This apparent restriction does lead to a greater likelihood of the syntax of
                each choice being consistent.</para>
            <para>Here is an example of a change to an array of strings.<table frame="all"
                    rowsep="1" colsep="1">
                    <title>JSON array value change</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3" align="left">
                        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.05*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.1*"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>A.txt</entry>
                                <entry>O.txt</entry>
                                <entry>B.txt</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <programlisting  language="javascript">["one", "two"]</programlisting>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <programlisting  language="javascript">["one"]</programlisting>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <programlisting  language="javascript">["three", "four"]</programlisting>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>This could be represented as shown below. Note here that we are not showing
                the result of running 'diff3 -m' but rather we have run an XML aware comparison so
                we have results that we want to express in the diff3 format.
                <screen xml:space="preserve">[
&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; A.txt
"one", "two"
||||||| O.txt
"one"
=======
"three", "four"
>>>>>>> B.txt
]</screen></para>
            <para>The above will produce syntactically correct results though it is not ideal
                because it would be more natural to choose the values separately rather than as a
                complete list. This can be achieved with diff3x as shown below. Here we have been
                able to perform the merge automatically, there are no conflicts but clearly it is
                useful for the user to see these and have the option to undo or change a
                choice.</para>
            <para>We introduce here a third type of choice, the <code language="xml">&lt;autoInclude></code>. This is a choice
                that we do not expect the user to review but rather it is a single option that is
                chosen automatically based on one or more other selections. In this case, the commas
                are inserted only when they are needed.</para>
            <para><programlisting language="xml">&lt;diff3x a="A.txt" b="B.txt" o="O.txt">
[
&lt;choice2>
  &lt;ao id="ao42">"one"&lt;/ao>
  &lt;b id="b44" include="true">&lt;/b>&lt;/choice2>
&lt;autoInclude select="AND(ao42 a52)">, &lt;/autoInclude>
&lt;choice2>
  &lt;a id="a52" include="true">"two"&lt;/a>
  &lt;ob id="ob53">&lt;/ob>&lt;/choice2>
&lt;autoInclude select="AND(OR(ao42 a52) b62)">, &lt;/autoInclude>
&lt;choice2>
  &lt;b id="b62" include="true">"three", "four"&lt;/b>
  &lt;ao id="ao63">&lt;/ao>&lt;/choice2>
]&lt;/diff3>

Result of this choice is:
["two", "three", "four"]</programlisting>This
                is more complex in getting the logic correct for insertion of commas. XML users will
                be pleased that XML attributes are not comma separated!</para>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="pres">
        <title>Preserving well-formed tree structure in diff3x</title>
        <para>In this section we explore the issues of preserving the well-formed structure of XML
            when presenting choices in diff3x.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Representing XML Element Tag Change in diff3x</title>
            <para>XML tags present a problem for diff3 format in that it is in general not possible
        to ensure a well-formed result without unacceptable duplication of content. To handle tag
        changes in diff3x we need to treat the XML payload, i.e. the XML that is the subject of
        change, as text and so escape it with CDATA markers. Later in this paper we look at treating
        an XML payload as XML, which is more natural but as we shall see, it is not possible to
        represent tag changes in that approach.</para>
            <para>Here is an example of a change of structure.<table frame="all" rowsep="1"
                    colsep="1">
                    <title>XML tag change</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3" align="left">
                        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.05*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.1*"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>A.txt</entry>
                                <entry>O.txt</entry>
                                <entry>B.txt</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;p>This is a long
paragraph where
&lt;strong>most of
it has been made 
either bold or 
italic, but the rest 
of the paragraph 
remains unchanged - 
there is no change 
to the text so
we do not want it 
duplicated&lt;/strong>.
&lt;/p></programlisting>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;p>This is a long
paragraph where
most of
it has been made 
either bold or 
italic, but the rest 
of the paragraph 
remains unchanged - 
there is no change 
to the text so
we do not want it 
duplicated.
&lt;/p></programlisting>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;p>This is a long
paragraph where
&lt;italic>most of
it has been made 
either bold or 
italic, but the rest 
of the paragraph 
remains unchanged - 
there is no change 
to the text so
we do not want it 
duplicated&lt;/italic>.
&lt;/p></programlisting>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>This could be represented as shown below, but there is duplication of
                unchanged text which is confusing because if there had been a small change the user
                would have found it difficult to see. Note that in this example the payload is XML
                but this is not seen as part of the XML of the carrier, the payload is treated as
                text because it is enclosed in the CDATA
                sections.<programlisting language="xml">&lt;diff3x a="A.txt" b="B.txt" o="O.txt">&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p>This is a long paragraph 
where ]]&gt;
&lt;choice3>
&lt;a>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;strong>most of it has 
been made either bold or
italic, but the rest of 
the paragraph remains 
unchanged - there is no 
change to the text so
we do not want it 
duplicated&lt;/strong>
]]&gt;&lt;/a>
&lt;o>&lt;![CDATA[most of it has 
been made either bold or
italic, but the rest of 
the paragraph remains 
unchanged - there is no 
change to the text so
we do not want it 
duplicated]]&gt;&lt;/o>
&lt;b>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;italic>most of it has 
been made either bold or
italic, but the rest of 
the paragraph remains 
unchanged - there is no 
change to the text so
we do not want it 
duplicated&lt;/italic>
]]&gt;&lt;/b>&lt;/choice3>
&lt;![CDATA[. &lt;/p>]]&gt;
&lt;/diff3x></programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>We can improve this significantly and use the id attributes as described above to
                ensure consistent choices. In this case we have given the options within the two
                connected choices an id value. Thus if option <code language="xml">&lt;a></code> is selected in one choice with
                id="a42" then the choice with id="a420" is automatically selected. We have also
                added 'vice versa' attributes so that the same would happen the other way round: if
                the end tag was selected then the corresponding start tag would also be
                selected.<programlisting language="xml">&lt;diff3x a="A.txt" b="B.txt" o="O.txt">&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p>This is a long paragraph 
where ]]&gt;
&lt;choice3 >
&lt;a id="a42" select="a420" include="true">&lt;![CDATA[&lt;strong>]]&gt;&lt;/a>
&lt;o/>
&lt;b id="b43" select="b430">&lt;![CDATA[&lt;italic>]]&gt;&lt;/b>&lt;/choice3>
most of it has 
been made either bold or
italic, but the rest of 
the paragraph remains 
unchanged - there is no 
change to the text so
we do not want it 
duplicated
&lt;choice3>
&lt;b select="b43" id="b430">&lt;![CDATA[&lt;/italic>]]&gt;&lt;/b>
&lt;o/>
&lt;a select="a42" id="a420">&lt;![CDATA[&lt;/strong>]]&gt;&lt;/a>&lt;/choice3>
&lt;![CDATA[. &lt;/p>]]&gt;
&lt;/diff3x></programlisting>If
                the GUI tool allowed multiple options to be selected, then both <code language="xml">&lt;strong></code> and
                <code language="xml">&lt;italic></code> could be selected - provided of course they appeared in the correct
                nested order. We have assumed that the user would need to have the knowledge to know
                if the selection of two options was appropriate.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Representing XML Attribute Change in diff3x</title>
            <para>XML attributes present a particular challenge for diff3 format, and this can be
                improved using an XML representation. </para>
            <para>It is worth noting an issue with the diff3 format in this situation, because it is
                quite subtle but one that we can resolve in diff3x. The lines in the input files at
                which all three files align (the lines are all equal) are considered 'anchor'
                points. All of the lines between anchor points is considered to be a single choice -
                and when there is some kind of conflict then the choice is left for the user to
                select. The interesting consequence of this structure is that it is not possible to
                have two consecutive choices without a separator which requires a commonality
                between all three files, i.e. an anchor point. For structured data it would be
                natural, for example, to provide choices about attributes in a manner that allows
                each attribute to be chosen separately, but the diff3 format dictates that two
                adjacent changes are seen as one choice. </para>
            <para>We can improve this with diff3x because we can easily have adjacent choices
                without any ambiguity.</para>
            <para>
                <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1">
                    <title>XML Attribute value change</title>
                    <tgroup cols="3" align="left">
                        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.05*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
                        <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.1*"/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>A.txt</entry>
                                <entry>O.txt</entry>
                                <entry>B.txt</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>
                                    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;span class="two" 
  dir="rtr" id="23"></programlisting>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;span class="one" 
  id="23" dir="TBA"></programlisting>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>
                                    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;span id="23" 
  class="three" dir="ltr"></programlisting>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>
            </para>
            <para>These changes can be represented in diff3x as shown
        below.<programlisting language="xml">&lt;diff3x a="A.txt" b="B.txt" o="O.txt">
&lt;![CDATA[&lt;span id="23"]]&gt;
&lt;choice3>
&lt;a>class="two"&lt;/a>
&lt;o>class="one"&lt;/o>
&lt;b>class="three"&lt;/b>&lt;/choice3>

&lt;choice3>
&lt;a>dir="rtr"&lt;/a>
&lt;o>dir="TBA"&lt;/o>
&lt;b>dir="ltr"&lt;/b>&lt;/choice3>
&lt;![CDATA[&lt;/span>]]&gt;&lt;/diff3x></programlisting>There
        is another representation that takes the common attribute name out of the choice but this
        may be less easy for a user to see what is happening by inspection of the diff3x but a GUI
        could provide an intuitive interface. For illustration, in the first class attribute we have
        included the attribute value quotation marks in the options, and for the dir attribute we
        have put them outside - this is a matter of choice, either approach can be represented by
        diff3x.<programlisting language="xml">&lt;diff3x a="A.txt" b="B.txt" o="O.txt">
&lt;![CDATA[&lt;span 
class=]]&gt;&lt;choice3>&lt;a>"two"&lt;/a>
                &lt;o>"one"&lt;/o>
                &lt;b>"three"&lt;/b>&lt;/choice3>
dir="&lt;choice3>&lt;a>rtr&lt;/a>
            &lt;o>TBA&lt;/o>
            &lt;b>ltr&lt;/b>&lt;/choice3>"
&lt;![CDATA[&lt;/span>]]&gt;&lt;/diff3x></programlisting>
      </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Nested Changes</title>
        <para>As diff3x is an XML representation we here consider going one step further and making
            use of the fact that the representation is hierarchical to support hierarchical or
            'nested' change. A nested change is a change in one branch that modifies something that
            has been removed in another branch.</para>
        <para>We will look at an XML example, showing nested changes. </para>
        <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1">
            <title>XML nested data example</title>
            <tgroup cols="3" align="left">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*" align="left"/>
                <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*" align="left"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry colname="c1">A.xml</entry>
                        <entry colname="c2">O.xml</entry>
                        <entry colname="c3">B.xml</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry colname="c1">
                            <programlisting language="xml" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<author>
<personname>
 <first>Nigel</first>
 <last>Whitaker</last>
</personname>
<address>
 <ph>01684 532141</ph>
 <st>Geraldine Rd</st>
 <city>Malvern</city>
 <country>UK</country>
 <post>WR14 3SZ</post>
</address>
</author>]]></programlisting>
                        </entry>
                        <entry colname="c2">
                            <programlisting language="xml" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<author>
<personname>
 <first>Nigel</first>
 <last>Whitaker</last>
</personname>
<address>
    
 <st>Geraldine Rd</st>
 <city>Malvern</city>
 <country>UK</country>
 <post>WR14 3SZ</post>
</address>
</author>]]></programlisting>
                        </entry>
                        <entry colname="c3">
                            <programlisting language="xml"  xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<author>
<personname>
 <first>Nigel</first>
 <last>Whitaker</last>
</personname>







</author>]]></programlisting>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>In the above example one branch, <filename>B.xml</filename>, has deleted the
                <code>address</code> sub-tree which the other branch has modified with an added
                <code>phone</code> number.  As we are now using an XML representation that has a
            tree structure we can also make use of this structure in the result. </para>
        <para>In order to distinguish between a simple <code language="xml">&lt;ao></code> option and a nested choice, we
            introduce the <code language="xml">&lt;aoChoice></code> element. This is a mixed content element that can include
            <code language="xml">&lt;a></code> or <code language="xml">&lt;o></code> elements as well as text.</para>
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<d:diff3x a="A.xml" b="B.xml" o="O.xml"><![CDATA[
<author>
<personname>
 <first>Nigel</first>
 <last>Whitaker</last>
</personname>]]]]>>
&lt;d:choice3>
 &lt;d:aoChoice include="true">&lt;![CDATA[
   &lt;address>]]&gt;
     &lt;d:a>&lt;![CDATA[
      &lt;ph>+44 1684 532141&lt;/ph>]]&gt;
     &lt;/d:a>
    &lt;![CDATA[
    &lt;st>Geraldine Rd&lt;/st>
    &lt;city>Malvern&lt;/city>
    &lt;country>UK&lt;/country>
    &lt;post>WR14 3SZ&lt;/post>
   &lt;/address>]]&gt;
  &lt;/d:aoChoice>
  &lt;d:bChoice/>
 &lt;/d:choice3>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;/author>]]&gt;
&lt;/d:diff3x></programlisting>
        <para>Here we can see that by allowing nested change we can avoid the repetition and make it
            easier for a human to understand. However, in order to support this in the format we
            have to introduce quite a number of new elements and different rules. This adds to the
            complexity of the format and moves us a lot further away from the original elegant
            simplicity of diff3. Keeping diff3x as simple as possible seems preferable to including
            the ability to represent a subset of changes as nested changes. </para>
        <para>For this reason we have elected not to include the ability to represent nested changes
            in diff3x.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Should an XML Payload be represented as XML or text?</title>
        <para>If our payload is XML, and our carrier is XML, does it make sense to embed the payload
            as XML rather than text? At first sight this seems to be an attractive proposition, and
            an example is shown below. For clarity we have put the diff3x elements into their own
            namespace, using a d: prefix.</para>
        <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1">
            <title>XML data example</title>
            <tgroup cols="3" align="left">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*" align="left"/>
                <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*" align="left"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry colname="c1">A.xml</entry>
                        <entry colname="c2">O.xml</entry>
                        <entry colname="c3">B.xml</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry colname="c1">
                            <programlisting language="xml" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<author>
<personname>
 <first>Nigel</first>
 <last>Whitaker</last>
</personname>
<address>
 <st>Geraldine Rd</st>
 <city>Malvern</city>
 <country>UK</country>
    
</address>
</author>]]></programlisting>
                        </entry>
                        <entry colname="c2">
                            <programlisting language="xml" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<author>
<personname>
 <first>Nigel</first>
 <last>Whitaker</last>
</personname>
<address>
 <st>Geraldine Rd</st>
 <city>Malvern</city>
 <country>UK</country>
 <post>WR14 3SZ</post> 
</address>
</author>]]></programlisting>
                        </entry>
                        <entry colname="c3">
                            <programlisting language="xml" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<author>
<personname>
 <first>Nigel</first>
 <last>Whitaker</last>
</personname>
<address>
 <st>Geraldine Rd</st>
 <city>Malvern</city>
 <country>UK</country>
 <post>PQ9 5XY</post> 
</address>
</author>]]></programlisting>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>This could be embedded in the XML diff3x carrier as shown below.</para>
        <programlisting language="xml" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<d:diff3x a="A.xml" b="B.xml" o="O.xml">
<author>
<personname>
  <first>Nigel</first>
  <last>Whitaker</last>
</personname>
<address>
 <st>Geraldine Rd</st>
 <city>Malvern</city>
 <country>UK</country>
 <d:choice3>
  <d:a/>
  <d:o>
   <post>WR14 3SZ</post>
  </d:o>
  <d:b>
   <post>PQ9 5XY</post>
  </d:b>
 </d:choice3>
</address>
</author>
</d:diff3x>]]></programlisting>
        <para>This looks good and useful, but it has limitations. The main one is that it would not
      be possible to show changes to attributes in situ, even if we resorted to XML processing
      instructions. Other approaches to this include representing attribute change by introducing an
      XML element immediately following the end of the start tag.</para>
        <para>Also, it would not be possible to show changes to element tags, e.g. if a <code language="xml">&lt;bold></code>
            was changed to <code language="xml">&lt;italic></code>. </para>
        <para>These limitations could be overcome by making the diff3x more complex but there is no
            good reason to do this because it takes away the primary purpose of the diff3x carrier,
            which is to represent changes to a text file. As an XML payload can be considered to be
            a text file we should treat it as such to be consistent with the handling of JSON or any
            other payload. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Saving Selected Options</title>
        <para>Some choices are for a user to decide which option(s) to include, others can be
            included automatically either as non-conflicting changes or as a direct result of other
            selections. If we are able to indicate in the format which options are currently
            selected, then we can save the state of the document during the resolution process. In
            addition, this would allow a user to change which option is selected in a choice. It
            would be advantageous for a GUI to allow not only a single option to be selected but two
            or more options - for example if A and B have added something different at the same
            position it may be correct to select neither, one or both options.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Comparing diff3 format with diff3x</title>
        <para>Although human readability is not the prime concern, it is worth looking at how the
      files might appear. The table below shows the example first used in <xref linkend="mismatched-sequences"/> as diff3 and the
      corresponding file in diff3x. We have not included the CDATA markers in XML here, but have
      added an xml:space="preserve" attribute indirectly via the schema.<table frame="all"
        rowsep="1" colsep="1">
        <title>diff3 and diff3x representations</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.05*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>diff3</entry>
              <entry>diff3x (XML)</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <screen xml:space="preserve">1
4
5
2
&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt; A.txt
3
||||||| O.txt
3
4
5
=======
4
5
3
>>>>>>> B.txt
6</screen>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <programlisting language="xml">&lt;diff3x a="A.txt" b="B.txt" 
    o="O.txt">1
4
5
2&lt;choice3>&lt;a>
3&lt;/a>&lt;o>
3
4
5&lt;/o>&lt;b>
4
5
3&lt;/b>&lt;/choice3>
6&lt;/diff3x></programlisting>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table></para>
        <para>It is worth noting that another advantage of the diff3x representation is that choices
            within a line can be represented quite naturally, so this overcomes the significant
            limitation of diff3 which is only able to show changes to a complete line. <table
                frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1">
                <title>Characteristics of diff3 and diff3x</title>
                <tgroup cols="4" align="left">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="3.22*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.26*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.22*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c5" colnum="4" colwidth="4*"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Characteristic</emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>diff3</entry>
                            <entry>diff3x</entry>
                            <entry>Comment</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>No processing needed for unchanged file</entry>
                            <entry>***</entry>
                            <entry>**</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Preserve line structure</entry>
                            <entry>***</entry>
                            <entry>***</entry>
                            <entry>XML needs CDATA</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Good for text editor (by hand)</entry>
                            <entry>**</entry>
                            <entry>*</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Intelligent changes</entry>
                            <entry>**</entry>
                            <entry>***</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Nested changes</entry>
                            <entry>*</entry>
                            <entry>***</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Changes within a line</entry>
                            <entry>*</entry>
                            <entry>***</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Show all resolved merges</entry>
                            <entry>*</entry>
                            <entry>***</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Show changes to JSON data</entry>
                            <entry>**</entry>
                            <entry>***</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Show changes to XML data</entry>
                            <entry>*</entry>
                            <entry>***</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Process the changes in the format of the native payload</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>*</entry>
                            <entry>Important to note that this is really not possible - a delta
                                format in the native format is needed.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table></para>
        <para>The table does show significant advantages of having an XML representation of diff3
            when communicating merge results from a merge driver to a GUI mergetool.   </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Future work</title>
      <para>In previous conferences and events we have shown and discussed different approaches to
      resolving and processing merge results using XML based technologies. We have shown a conflict
      resolver using an OxygenXML plugin and one based on Schematron Quick Fixes (SQF) <biblioref
        linkend="SQF"/>. These work well with an XML payload, but aren't directly usable with other
      forms of structured content such as JSON. At DeltaXML we are finding that customers want to
      evaluate our tools in the browser and fewer users are willing to download and install a ZIP
      package with our code/APIs. We have tools/services for XML and JSON and display comparison and
      merge results in the browser, but we do not provide an interactive merge resolver. Using
      diff3x would help to provide this capability for both XML, JSON and potentially other
      structured formats. </para>

      <para>In <biblioref linkend="git-prague"/> we discussed what we feel are inefficiencies/shortcomings in many git workflows where a
      mergetool would repeat the work done in the merge driver, often inconsistently.  The format presented here is one possible solution
      that could be used to address these issues.  This would allow effort spent understanding structured merged techniques to be
      concentrated/shared and not repeated in different merge tools.  We would welcome
      feedback from the wider git user community and also from those interested in mergetools.</para>
    </section>


    <section>
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <para>In this paper we have introduced an XML update to diff3 which we have called diff3x.
            With diff3x, we can integrate more modern structure-aware comparison tools and represent
            choices that are consistent with the structure and more likely to provide well-formed or
            valid results. </para>
        <para>We have considered the representation of nested changes but concluded that the
            additional complexity to the diff3x format is unlikely to be worth the small gain. </para>
        <para>The diff3x format can take plain text as its payload. If the payload is XML it would
            need to be escaped for example with CDATA and treated as text. We considered whether, if
            the payload is also XML, this could be treated as XML and although this is possible we
            concluded that treating an XML payload as text has the advantage that tag changes and
            attribute changes can be represented directly in situ. Our experience with XML tools and
            technologies has allowed us to develop XML-centric resolvers, but these have the
            limitation that they do not work with JSON and other non-XML formats. They still have
            benefits and their applications, for example when considering nested change or n-way
            merge. As such they complement the benefits of diff3x.</para>
        <para>In a related paper [<biblioref linkend="git-prague"/>] we identified some issues in version
            control systems that caused inconsistency and confusion to users. One solution to those
            issues relies on separating the merge driver from subsequent conflict resolution tools
            or 'merge tools'. The diff3x format proposed here would work well for data exchange
            between these two steps. This is important because it separates knowledge of the format
            and structure of a file from a GUI designed to allow the acceptance of changes or the
            resolution of conflict thus enabling a single GUI to handle many different file
            structures in a consistent way.</para>
        <para>The intention of diff3x is to provide a richer format than diff3 for the exchange of
            differences and conflicts in text files. The advantages of diff3x over diff3 include the
            following:</para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Recording user selections of options: this provides both the facility to
                        save changes during a merge resolution session and providing an audit record
                        of the choices made.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Connected options: this provides the ability for the selection of one
                        option to trigger the selection of another connected option, e.g. when a
                        start tag is selected the corresponding end tag is also included.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Auto include of text: this provides for certain text to be automatically
                        included if certain options are selected, e.g. so that appropriate
                        separators could be included.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>We have shown that improvements to the representation of change for structured data is
            possible and desirable. Changing the existing diff3 format proved to be awkward and
            limited, so this move directly to a markup representation using XML is a better
            approach. In working this through in more detail in this paper we have identified other
            advantages to make it easier for users to accept or reject changes in a way that is
            consistent with the underlying structure of the data.</para>
    </section>
    <bibliography>
        <title>References</title>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="diff3format" xreflabel="1">
            <citetitle><link xlink:href="https://markupuk.org/2019/Markup-UK-2019-proceedings.pdf#page=87">
                An Improved diff3 Format for Changes and Conflicts in Tree Structures.</link></citetitle>
        </bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="diffutils" xreflabel="2">
            <citetitle><link xlink:href="https://www.gnu.org/software/diffutils">GNU DiffUtil -
                Comparing and Merging Files.</link></citetitle>
        </bibliomixed>
        
        <bibliomixed xml:id="FormalDiff3" xreflabel="3">Khanna S., Kunal K.,
            Pierce B.C. (2007) <citetitle><link
                xlink:href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007%2F978-3-540-77050-3_40">A
                Formal Investigation of Diff3. In: Arvind V., Prasad S. (eds) FSTTCS 2007:
                Foundations of Software Technology and Theoretical Computer Science. FSTTCS
                2007. Lecture Notes in Computer Science, vol 4855. Springer, Berlin, Heidelberg
            </link></citetitle></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="SQF" xreflabel="4"><citetitle>
                <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.schematron-quickfix.com/"
                    >Schematron QuickFix </link></citetitle>
        </bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="git-prague" xreflabel="5"> Robin La Fontaine and
            Nigel Whitaker <citetitle>
                <link
                    xlink:href=" http://archive.xmlprague.cz/2019/files/xmlprague-2019-proceedings.pdf#page=175"
                    >Merge and Graft: Two Twins That Need To Grow Apart</link></citetitle>
        </bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
</article>
