<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="resources/css/paper.css"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
	<info>
		<title>Beyond the brick, for the past in the future, you find the
			archive!</title>
		<author>
			<personname>Karin Bredenberg</personname>
			<email>karin.bredenberg@riksarkivet.se</email>
			<uri><link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1627-2361"
					xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></uri>
			<personblurb>
				<para><emphasis role="bold">Karin Bredenberg</emphasis> is a Senior Technical
					Advisor on metadata at the Swedish National Archives. She currently serves as
					the chair of PREMIS EC, co-chair of TS EAS, chair of the DILCIS Board as well as
					a member of the METS Board. Currently Bredenberg is the activity lead for
					specifications in the project E-ARK4ALL and the European Commission’s eArchiving
					Building block.</para>
			</personblurb>
			<affiliation>
				<jobtitle>Senior Technical Advisor metadata</jobtitle>
				<orgname>National Archives of Sweden</orgname>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<personname>Jaime Kaminski</personname>
			<email>j.kaminski@brighton.ac.uk</email>
			<uri><link xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2907-0128"
					xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/></uri>
			<personblurb>
				<para><emphasis role="bold">Jaime Kaminski</emphasis> BA, MA, PhD, is a senior
					lecturer at the University of Brighton. For the last 14 years, he has been
					researching in the field of Digital Humanities where he has been working on
					EC-funded projects including EPOCH, 3D-COFORM, V-MUST, E-RHIS, ROMOR, E-ARK and
					E-ARK4ALL, as well as the UKRO-funded SEAHA project. Before joining academia, he
					spent 7 years as a technical briefings manager and senior technology analyst for
					a Blue Chip ICT consultancy.</para>
			</personblurb>
			<affiliation>
				<jobtitle>Senior Lecturer</jobtitle>
				<orgname>University of Brighton</orgname>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<keywordset>
			<keyword>Archives</keyword>
			<keyword>metadata</keyword>
			<keyword>standards</keyword>
			<keyword>de-facto standards</keyword>
			<keyword>specifications</keyword>
			<keyword>eArchiving building block</keyword>
			<keyword>DILCIS Board</keyword>
			<keyword>E-ARK</keyword>
			<keyword>XML</keyword>
			<keyword>XML-schema</keyword>
			<keyword>Schematron</keyword>
			<keyword>CITS</keyword>
			<keyword>CSIP</keyword>
			<keyword>SIARD</keyword>
			<keyword>ERMS</keyword>
			<keyword>Geospatialdata</keyword>
		</keywordset>
		<abstract>
			<para>The statement that XML is dead<anchor xml:id="_ftnref1"/>[1] is as wrong as
				celebrating Christmas on midsummer night’s eve! At least in our opinion. Imagine
				making an archival soup based on international standards using XML, with one
				municipal archive, two regional archives, five national archives and the European
				Commission’s eArchiving Building block thrown into the mix. This is what we are
				going to attempt, let us set the stage and take you through the recipe!</para>
			<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn1"/>[1]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
					xlink:href="https://developpaper.com/is-xml-dead/"
					>https://developpaper.com/is-xml-dead/</link> is a starting point for getting
				more information regarding the statment.</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>
	<section>
		<title>Archives</title>
		<para>In our world the organisation responsible for saving the records of an organisational
			unit like documents or other artefacts that gives us our history is the archive. The
			archives exist in different levels of our society, in companies, in municipalities, in
			regions and at national levels as national archives. This means that the big difference
			between a library and an archive is seen in the library being responsible for the
			printed word. Today when the records are digital records the challenges to keep them has
			grown from taking care of paper to handling migration of records from obsolete formats,
			authenticity of the record so its reliable and most of all making sure the record is
			readable in the future considering format and available hardware.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Building Blocks</title>
		<para>Let’s start with Connecting Europe Facility<anchor xml:id="_ftnref2"/>[2] and its
			Building Blocks<anchor xml:id="_ftnref3"/>[3], what are they? The European Union realise
			that internet and digital technologies are transforming our world. A true statement.
			They also see is that the digital landscape is becoming more diverse, creating
			challenges for cross-border interoperability and intercommunication. Europe is about
			working together but, Europeans still face barriers when using (cross-border) online
			tools and services. The implications are considerable. EU citizens can miss out on goods
			and services and businesses in the EU miss out on market potential, while also the
			different governments in EU cannot fully benefit from digital technologies. The EU has
			therefore described the Digital Single Market<anchor xml:id="_ftnref4"/>[4] (DSM)
			through which it aims to overcome these challenges by creating the right environment for
			digital networks and services to flourish. The DSM is not only achieved by setting the
			right regulatory conditions, but also by providing cross-border digital infrastructures
			and services. So, to support the DSM, the Connecting Europe Facility (CEF) programme is
			funding a set of generic and reusable Digital Service Infrastructures (DSI), also known
			as Building Blocks. The CEF building blocks offer basic capabilities that can be reused
			in any European project to facilitate the delivery of digital public services across
			borders and sectors. Currently, there are eight building blocks: Big Data Test
			Infrastructure, Context Broker, eArchiving, eDelivery, eID, eInvoicing, eSignature and
			eTranslation. The main part of CEF is a Core Service Platform, provided and maintained
			by the European Commission. Depending on the building block, the Core Service Platform
			may include technical specifications, sample software and supporting services (funding
			for the European Commission). The CEF building blocks offer basic capabilities that can
			be used in any European project to facilitate the delivery of digital public services
			across borders. The basis for the CEF Building Blocks are interoperability agreements
			between European Union member states. The aim of the Building Blocks is thus to ensure
			interoperability between IT systems so that citizens, businesses and administrations can
			benefit from seamless digital public services wherever they may be in Europe.</para>
		<para><mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="Images/BuildingBlocks.PNG" scale="40" scalefit="0"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>The Building block layers</phrase>
			</textobject>
			<caption>
				<para>The Building block layers.</para>
			</caption>
		</mediaobject>
			</para>
		<para>For each building block the European Commission provides a Core Service Platform which
			consists of three layers:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>At the core of each building block is a layer of technical specifications and
					standards that have to be complied with;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>To facilitate the implementation of the technical specifications and
					standards, a layer of sample software that complies with them and is meant for
					reuse (for certain building blocks only);</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>To facilitate the adoption of the technical specifications and standards, a
					layer of services (e.g. conformance testing, help desks, onboarding services,
					etc.) meant for use (which varies depending on the Building Block).</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>All this means that the Building Blocks can be combined and used in projects in any
			domain or sector at European, national or local level.</para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn2"/>[2]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://ec.europa.eu/digital-single-market/en/connecting-europe-facility"
				>https://ec.europa.eu/digital-single-market/en/connecting-europe-facility</link></para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn3"/>[3]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://ec.europa.eu/cefdigital/wiki/display/CEFDIGITAL/CEF+Digital+Home"
				>https://ec.europa.eu/cefdigital/wiki/display/CEFDIGITAL/CEF+Digital+Home</link></para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn4"/>[4]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://ec.europa.eu/digital-single-market/en"
				>https://ec.europa.eu/digital-single-market/en</link></para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>eArchiving Building Block</title>
		<para>For the archives and others transferring information the newly set up eArchiving
			building block <anchor xml:id="_ftnref5"/>[5]is the important component in protecting
			our history. The aim of eArchiving is to provide the core specifications, software,
			training and knowledge to help data creators, software developers and digital archives
			tackle the challenge of short, medium and long-term data management and reuse in a
			sustainable, authentic, cost-efficient, manageable and interoperable way. The core of
			eArchiving is formed by Information Package specifications which describe a common
			format for storing bulk data and metadata in a platform-independent, authentic and
			long-term understandable way. The specifications are ideal for migrating long-term
			valuable data between generations of information systems, transferring data to dedicated
			long-term repositories (i.e. digital archives), or preserving and reusing data over
			extended (and shorter) periods of time and generations of software systems. Next to the
			specifications eArchiving offers a set of sample software to demonstrate the format in
			different scenarios and business environments, and consultancy in regard to long-term
			digital preservation risks and their mitigation.</para>
		<para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="Images/eArchiving%20services%20v2%20-%20with%20CS%20IP%20and%20CS%20CT.png" scale="50" scalefit="0"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>The eArchiving building block and its services and specifications</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>
					<para>The eArchiving building block and its services and specifications.</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn5"/>[5]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://ec.europa.eu/cefdigital/wiki/display/CEFDIGITAL/eArchiving"
				>https://ec.europa.eu/cefdigital/wiki/display/CEFDIGITAL/eArchiving</link></para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Long-term preservation of information</title>
		<para>Continuing from the specifications in the building block XML has long been the go-to
			format for the long-term preservation of information, mainly because it can structure
			information in a way that isunderstandable to both humans and machines. There have been
			concerns and comments raised regarding Json taking over the role of XML. However, in the
			archival setting even if JSon is easier to use as a programmer in the long term XML wins
			because readable elements and attributes explaining the information or what we call
			content placed in the document. However, at the same time XML needs to be used wisely
			with the correct element and attribute names to facilitate the understanding of the
			human reading of the XML-document both now as well as in the future. There are also
			other formats used like tiff and pdf but for reuse of the information XML is the format
			to go to in most cases.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Use cases</title>
		<para>Our use case involves transferring information to different recipients. Information
			described with numerous ISO as well as <emphasis role="italic">de facto</emphasis>
			standards, all built around XML, which can be used for the transfer, storage and
			dissemination of information. Some of the most important use cases are shown in the
			following image.</para>
		<para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="Images/use_cases_full_scaled.jpg" scale="125" scalefit="0"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>The eArchiving use cases</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>
					<para>The eArchiving use cases.</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</para>
		<para>A short description of what we see in the image is that information is created in a
			system, the information is being exported as a number of different documents which can
			be sent to an electronic archive, being used by a researcher, published on-line,
			imported into a new system and so on.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Skill set</title>
		<para>And with that setting of uses cases and need for reuse in a lot of ways we can only
			make the conclusion that a modern archivist, or perhaps the more accurate title is
			information or records manager, needs to understand XML and more than one standard for
			handling the information for which they are the caretakers. Besides the need for knowing
			a lot of different technical languages there is also a need to speak the same language
			as the programmers who will aid you with creating export and import tools. A challenge
			still not fully addressed in either community. The language challenge is something all
			the different communities and professions working together need to start working with. A
			common solution is that every work place and profession has their own language making
			cross-border professional exchange almost impossible without a lot of extra meetings,
			things that can be avoided if a common vocabulary was agreed upon and communicated to
			all professions. Look, for example, at the term ‘archive’ which means “to transfer
			records from the individual or office of creation to a repository authorised to
			appraise, preserve, and provide access to those records”<anchor xml:id="_ftnref6"/>[6]
			in the archival setting and the meaning “to store data offline.”<anchor
				xml:id="_ftnref7"/>[7] in the programmer and more technical setting. A unification
			is needed and at the same time not easy to achieve due to the different professions lack
			of common foras for these kinds of discussions (let’s not forget that not speaking to
			each other is more common than we would like to imagine).</para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn6"/>[6]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://www2.archivists.org/glossary/terms/a/archive"
				>https://www2.archivists.org/glossary/terms/a/archive</link></para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn7"/>[7]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://www2.archivists.org/glossary/terms/a/archive"
				>https://www2.archivists.org/glossary/terms/a/archive</link></para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Standards, de facto standards and specifications</title>
		<para>Jenn Riley’s Visualization of the Metadata Universe<anchor xml:id="_ftnref8"/>[8]has been
			around for a while, but still gives the best overview of standardsused in the cultural
			sector, archives, libraries and museums. In the image there are numerous standards are
			displayed in the context of their function and where they are used.</para>
		<para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="Images/seeingstandards.png" scale="60" scalefit="0"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>The visualization of the Metadata Universe</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>
					<para>The visualization of the Metadata Universe by Jenn Riley. (The recommendation is to look on-line)</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</para>
		<para>Almost all standards on the metadata map created by Jenn Riley have an XML format
			available described with an DTD or an XML-schema. For the XML-schemas both the ISO
			standard RelaxNG as well as W3C XML-schema formats are used. The choice depends solely
			on the skills of the creator of the schema and at the same time it’s also common to
			ensure that all different type of schemas are available so transformations from RelaxNG
			to XML-schema and vice versa is often used. DTD are still around due to the fact that
			old software is still in use and they are based upon using a DTD. </para>
		<para>The most common way to use the standards is to write a specification which describes a
			profile for our use case of the standard which then in its turn are implemented in the
			setting you are operating. The best way of describing the use of profiles is the
			standard METS (more about that later) which requires the user to write a profile
			describing how it is used. </para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn8"/>[8]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="http://jennriley.com/metadatamap/"
				>http://jennriley.com/metadatamap/</link></para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>eArchiving Building block Specifications</title>
		<para>The story of eArchiving Building Block specifications originates at work starting at
			the National Archives of Sweden and being enhanced in the E-ARK project<anchor
				xml:id="_ftnref9"/>[9]. The project delivered 7 draft specifications which all built
			upon creating profiles of standards and de-facto standards, these can be split into 4
			specifications describing profiles of the standard METS and one for electronic records
			management, one for geodata and finally one for using the SIARD <anchor
				xml:id="_ftnref10"/>[10]standards. The project ended but no one wanted the work to be
			a usual project result, forgotten and not used so to make sure these specifications to
			not stop evolving the project created the “Digital Information LifeCycle
			Interoperability Standards Board” (DILCIS Board<anchor xml:id="_ftnref11"/>[11]). The
			board took over the specifications and have during the project E-ARK4ALL<anchor
				xml:id="_ftnref12"/>[12] (which are responsible for setting up and maintaining the
			eArchiving Building Block) brought them to a stabilised state and started the
			development of more specifications. A work carried out together with the experts of
			specific content so it’s the experts writing the specifications. The board is set up
			with currently eight members and are charged with the task of handling the
			specifications. The Board is at the same time the core producers of specifications to
			the eArchiving Building Block.</para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn9"/>[9]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://eark-project.com/">https://eark-project.com/</link></para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn10"/>[10]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://www.bar.admin.ch/bar/en/home/archiving/tools/siard-suite.html"
				>https://www.bar.admin.ch/bar/en/home/archiving/tools/siard-suite.html</link></para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn11"/>[11]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://dilcis.eu/">https://dilcis.eu/</link></para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn12"/>[12]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://e-ark4all.eu/">https://e-ark4all.eu/</link></para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>The eArchiving reference model setting</title>
		<para>When we consider the European Commission’s new eArchiving Building Block and that its
			evident that at its core are specifications based upon formats expressed in XML. The
			entireBuildingBlockrevolves around transfers of information where the final transfer is
			to the archives, but nothing prevents these transfers occurring earlier in the
			information lifecycle. The e-archive is built upon the Reference Model for an Open Archival Information System (OAIS Reference Model)<anchor
				xml:id="_ftnref13"/>[13]and its use of information packages, the Submission
			Information Package (SIP), the Archival Information Package (AIP) and the Dissemination
			Information Package (DIP). There are more parts described in the reference model but the
			core part used in the specifications are the information packages.</para>
		<para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="Images/CSIP_fig_1_oais_ele_ip.svg" scale="50" scalefit="0"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>The OAIS reference model</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>
					<para>The OAIS reference model.</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</para>
		<para>The different packages in the OAIS reference model are within the eArchiving Building
			Block described or get their inventory or manifest stated with the Metadata Encoding and
			Transmission Standard (METS)<anchor xml:id="_ftnref14"/>[14] which uses XML as the format
			for creating the readable text. (For the AIP it might be a format internal to the
			archival system you are using but that is another paper.) This way both machines and
			humans can understand the package (we do have some extra principles which aid with what
			constitutes a package). METS itself is a rather open standard with only one mandatory
			element being a structural description of the package. The standards also demand the
			creation of a profile for the exact use case describing the use of the standard and its
			elements and attributes. The profile for the eArchiving Building Block requires besides
			the METS XML-schema an extension XML-schema and validation rules in Schematron. The
			difficulties occur when the common user doesnot know how to validate the XML in
			combination with Schematron due to poor or no knowledge of either XML or Schematron and
			not having access to a person with the knowledge. We must not forget that Schematron
			adds its owncomplexities when it is combined with a non-relaxNG schema. A complexity
			that can be overwhelming when you don’t know XML at all or just a basic understanding.
			This gives that numerousguidance documents need to be created ranging from how to write
			XML to how to use a specification. And all this since you cannot count on the person
			implementing the specification and its validation to have the appropriate background
			knowledge. </para>
		<para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="Images/CS%20IP%20overview.png" scale="40" scalefit="0"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>The eArchiving building block and the different specifications building up a Information Package</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>
					<para>The eArchiving building block and the different specifications building up a Information Package. In the image the three different types of packages is seen.</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn13"/>[13]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://www.iso.org/standard/57284.html"
				>https://www.iso.org/standard/57284.html</link></para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn14"/>[14]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mets/"
				>http://www.loc.gov/standards/mets/</link></para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Content specifications</title>
		<para>Well, we now have a package described in XML, we need some content and maybe images,
			PDFs and information structured in XML that extends the information recorded in the
			package. This means we have one or more XML-documents to describe the information and
			its structure, and another XML-document to describe the whole package with all the
			content, but not the structure of the information itself. We can even handle a
			relational database in this way, extracting it in XML format and then packaging it in a
			SIP for transfer to the archive. Specifications of content are at the heart of the
			eArchiving Building Block, and the number of specifications is growing steadily. There
			are lots of different kinds of information that need to be described, luckily there are
			many specifications for describing information in XML, so there is no need to reinvent
			the wheel.</para>
		<para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="Images/CEF_Specifications.jpg" scale="40" scalefit="0"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>The eArchiving building block specifications</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>
					<para>The eArchiving building block specifications.</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</para>
		<para>In the image the content is described with the acronym CITS which means Content
			Information Type Specifications. Currently there are three available as described
			previously. </para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>A specification for electronic records management systems (ERMS), the
						specification uses a XML-schema as the format and is based upon several
						available records management standards which in their turn don’t have a
						common XML-format available which means the ERMS specification is the
						connection between the different standards and the export of information
						from a ERMS.<anchor xml:id="_ftnref15"/>[15]</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>A specification for geospatial data which uses the ISO standard for
						preservation of geospatial data in combination with the regulation within
						the union regarding geospatial data “the Inspire directive”. In the
						specification a description of geospatial data and what it is found together
						with how the description of the data is carried out since the geospatial
						system themselves export information in readable formats but lack
						descriptions making the information understandable in the
						future.<anchor xml:id="_ftnref16"/>[16]</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>A specification for how to place a relational database exported with the
						format SIARD in an information package. The format has been developed by the
						Swiss Federal Archives and is now a part of the DILCIS Boards
						responsibilities. The SIARD format is based upon export of the database as
						XML and several tools exist which aids with the task.<anchor
						xml:id="_ftnref17"/>[17]</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn15"/>[15]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://github.com/DILCISBoard/E-ARK-ERMS"
				>https://github.com/DILCISBoard/E-ARK-ERMS</link></para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn16"/>[16]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://github.com/DILCISBoard/E-ARK-Geodata"
				>https://github.com/DILCISBoard/E-ARK-Geodata</link></para>
		<para><anchor xml:id="_ftn17"/>[17]<link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
				xlink:href="https://github.com/DILCISBoard/SIARD"
				>https://github.com/DILCISBoard/SIARD</link></para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Basic soup recipe with a twist</title>
		<para>We started with you imagine the making of an archival soup based on international
			standards using XML, with one municipal archive, two regional archives, five national
			archives and the European Commission’s eArchiving Building block thrown into the mix. So
			how do we get this soup to be the “perfect” soup? We use core specifications based upon
			XML that can be enhanced the further down or closer to the user you get thus making the
			work and transfer to an archive a piece of cake.</para> 
		<para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="Images/Fig%201%20ERMS.svg" scale="25" scalefit="0"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>The specification enhancement layers.</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>
					<para>The specification enhancement layers.</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</para>	
			
			<para>So our soup gets transformed into the
			set of use cases which is suitable for different kinds of users as well as different
			kinds of information.</para>
		<para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="Images/LEvels%20of%20adaption.jpg" scale="125" scalefit="0"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>The specification user layers of adoption</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>
					<para>The specification user layers of adoption.</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</para>
		<para>The image shows us that the closer to the information and the implementation you get
			the more demands is added to make the information understandable in the future. We still
			are obliged to use the core set which means interoperability is achieved and at the same
			time the users own needs is an addition to enhance the core set.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Conclusion: Moving on from soup</title>
		<para>The archival soup isn’t in fact a soup it’s a core set of common specifications using
			a machine and human readable language which makes it possible for one municipal archive,
			two regional archives, five national archives and the European Commission’s eArchiving
			Building block to transfer information, store the information for “infinitive” time and
			deliver it to all different kind of users wanting to use the information, use the
			information for researchers, building applications, doing statistical reposts, prove who
			they are, all the things you can do with information. This is supported by the
			advantages of XML and its way of being readable both by machine and humans. That the
			XML-document can be opened in just a text editor means that it is easy to read our past
			both now and in the future. This means that the support for XML needs to exist now and
			further down the road even if we in the archival community as XML users do not take part
			in all working groups maintaining XML instead being more concerned about the standards,
				<emphasis role="italic">de facto</emphasis>standards or specifications based on XML
			so we can ensure the past being created now will be present in the future.</para>

	</section>

	<bibliography xml:id="karin-references">
		<bibliomixed> <abbrev>MDU</abbrev> <author>
			<personname><surname>Riley</surname><firstname>Jenn</firstname></personname>
		</author>: <title>Seeing standards: A visualization of the Metadata Universe</title>. Design: Devin Becker<date>2009-2010</date>, <orgname>Work funded by the Indiana University Libraries White Professional Development Award</orgname>. <bibliomisc><link
			xl:href="http://jennriley.com/metadatamap/"/></bibliomisc> </bibliomixed>
		
	</bibliography>

</article>
